It's no secret that jQuery's one of the most popular JavaScript libraries out there, and for good reason.
You can do an amazing number of things with it, increase your productivity, and quite honestly, have a lot
more fun along the way; especially if you have to deal with cross-browser types of issues.
Well if you've been wanting to learn jQuery, or have been putting it off and didn't know where to start,
you're in the right place. I'd like to welcome you to the jQuery Fundamentals course. My name's Dan Wahlin
with Pluralsight, and throughout this course I'm going to be covering all the key fundamentals that you need
to know to get started on maximizing your productivity with jQuery, dealing with cross-browser issues more
effectively, and many other things along the way. With jQuery we can select items in the DOM, we can handle
events, we can do AJAX calls, and the list goes on and on and on. And we'll be highlighting and covering
some of those key features throughout this course.
Now to get the most out of this course, you do need to have a background in JavaScript, so as long as
you're comfortable with the overall syntax you'll be fine. You do need a background in HTML and CSS as well.
Now, you don't have to be an expert at any of it, but as long as you're comfortable with what an HTML tag
is, what CSS is, what a CSS class is and those types of things, then you're getting quite a bit out of this
course because jQuery is all about manipulating HTML, CSS, and other aspects of your web page.
So let's go ahead and get started and jump in to module one and talk about why would we want to use jQuery
in the first place.