In this first module we're going to talk about some of the reasons you'd want to use jQuery, and some of
the features it provides out of the box. And then we're going to go into how we actually reference jQuery,
and there's a couple different ways you can do it, you'll see. We can actually load a script locally in a
web page, or we can use something called a CDN, or Content Delivery Network, and I'll talk about the pros
and cons of both approaches. From there we're going to talk about after you have jQuery referenced in a
page, how do you actually know when that page is loaded at runtime in the browser so that you can then use
jQuery to interact with the page; and it's called the Document Ready, and we'll talk about how that works
and why you'd need it. And then we'll wrap up with a quick tour of the jQuery documentation out there; it's
a very good thing to know, because, although I'll teach you all the key fundamentals you'll need in this
course, after you get done there's certainly going to be additional features you might want to add, and you
need to know where to go look those up and get more information about them.
So we'll talk about that in the jQuery documentation section. So let's go ahead and get started by talking
about why use jQuery, and what are some of the different features it provides.