Let's start things off by asking that all-important question of what is jQuery, and why would I want to use
it in the first place? Well, I asked the same exact question many years ago when I got started, and the
good news is, the more I dug into it the more impressed I was. So jQuery is just a single JavaScript file,
that's all it is; nothing more, nothing less, but it's a really powerful single JavaScript file, and it's
cross-browser, and that's why jQuery, at least in my opinion, took off many years ago when it first came
out, because we had to deal with IE 6, and then Firefox, and then Chrome started to come on the scene later,
and just a lot of issues there with cross-browser coding. Well jQuery makes it so you can focus on your
app; you don't have to worry if you're on Safari or Chrome or whatever it is, so unless you have a very
specific browser feature, jQuery's going to take care of it for you; whether it's finding things in the DOM,
or handling events, or making AJAX calls, it'll take care of the behind the scenes heavy lifting to figure
out what browser it is and how to deal with it. Now as far as features go, one of the most powerful
features it offers is called Selectors; this is the ability to select things in the DOM and then manipulate those.
And you'll see there's an entire Selector language with different expressions we can write that we'll be
covering later in the course, so it's an awesome feature that literally will save you hours over what we did
in the old days. When it comes to events, jQuery has a very rich event infrastructure, and as I mentioned,
it deals with browsers very nicely. You don't have to worry about Safari, Firefox, and all the others, you
can just write a single code base and know that your events are going to work and be handled appropriately.
In addition to that, we have very rich support for AJAX: Asynchronies JavaScript And XML.
And although we don't really use XML that much nowadays, you can really use jQuery to call back to a server
and get whatever data you'd like. Nowadays it's usually JSON data: JavaScript Object Notation, and later in
the course we'll be talking about that and how AJAX works with jQuery. And then finally in addition to
these features, and actually many others that I won't have time here to go into, there's a very rich
community of free jQuery plug-ins. So if you need something like a light box to display pictures, or you
want to touch-friendly way to swipe through pictures, or you want an auto-complete textbox that as they type
it pops down things that match up with what they've typed. You could certainly write all that by hand, but
there's thousands of plug-ins out there that you can plug into your page really quickly and get started
right off the bat without writing a lot of code.
Now, why use jQuery? Well, the cross-browser issue is probably one of the biggest reasons, but there's a
lot of different reasons actually, and I think when you go look at simple things like how would I find
multiple div's that have a class called foo on them? Well if you have modern browsers, you could use the
new Query Selector functionality, but if you have older browsers, there's really not a great way to do that.
Well jQuery makes that a piece of cake; with one simple and very concise line of code, you could find all
the div's that have a specific class on them, and you don't even have to write the looping code to do it.
Another question: how do you apply styles to multiple elements with one line of code?
Now it can be done with just pure vanilla, plain JavaScript, but you're definitely going to have to do some
looping and other operations. Well the jQuery with just a single, again very concise line of code, you can
apply styles or classes to multiple elements in the DOM. How do you handle events in a cross-browser manner?
Well, most of the modern browsers nowadays have a standard way to do that; we can just add an event
listener and it's pretty easy and not a lot of code. But, if you do still have to deal with some of the
older browsers, you'll know that things like IE 6 doesn't support events in the same way that they
should've, according to the spec anyway. So jQuery takes that headache out of the picture, and really, we
just don't want to deal with these cross-browser issues at all; we want to write our application, focus on
the logic, focus on the UI, and have fun doing it.
And that to me is where jQuery really shines; it makes client-side development fun again, because we don't
have to worry as much about the browser.