So how do you get started adding jQuery into a web page? Well, you can head off to jquery.com, and there's
two different options you can download. If you're going to be supporting IE 6 - 8 then you're probably
going to want to go with jQuery 1, and then there's 1.9, and the versions will change.
If you don't have to support IE 6 - 8 and you only want to go with modern browsers, then you can go with
jQuery 2.x, and that'd give you a more slimmed down version, it's more modular, and it's not going to have
all that overhead associated with some of the older browsers; so it's kind of a more lean script if you will.
Now from there all you have to do is reference the script in your web page; very, very simple, so go to
jquery.com, grab the appropriate version based on your requirements, and then add that script into your web
page. Now the editor that you use to do it can be really anything; it can be something as simple as
notepad, or WordPad, or whatever you like.
There's a lot of great editors out there; Visual Studio, Eclipse, Aptana, I like Sublime Text a lot,
WebStorm, and many, many others. Really you just need a text editor; the same thing you would use with HTML
for that matter, or CSS. So now that we've talked about how to get started, let's run off to jquery.com
real quick and take a look at it.
To work with jQuery you want to head over to jquery.com in your browser, and from the home page you'll see a
lot of the different features; Lightweight Footprint, CSS3 Compliant, Cross-Browser, as I've mentioned, and
right here is the important part though, we can download jQuery. And you'll notice that there's actually
two versions; now these versions will change over time of course, but right now it's v1.9.1, and 2.0.
And you may look at that and go, well, why are there two, and which one would I pick?
Well, the 1.9.1, or really any 1.x I'm going to say, is designed to be backward compatible, all the way back
to IE 6. Anything with a 2.x is going to be IE 9 or higher, and any of the modern browsers out there.
So if you need IE 6 through 8 support, you're going to go with a 1.x; otherwise, if you don't need that and
you just want to target the modern browsers out there, you can go with the 2.x, whatever that is.
So if I click on this, you'll see that I can now come on in and download either the 1.x or the 2.x.
Now you have a couple options here as well; the compressed version is going to be very, very small, it's
what we call the minified or minimized version, and it's all compressed up, unnecessary white space has been
removed, variables have been shortened, things like that to make it really small for production.
If you want to debug though and step through jQuery from your code, you might want to grab the uncompressed,
more readable version, and that's this version here. And we have that for the 1.x, and you can see the 2.x.
So let's assume that at work I still have IE 8 hanging around, which is often the case in a lot of big
corporations. Then I might grab the 1.x version, so I'm going to grab this one here, and I'm just going to
Save Link As, and then I can save it to wherever I'd like. And I'm just going to call this jquery.js to
keep it really simple, and save that. Now, all I have to do is go into my web page, and I have a very
simple one here, and either up in the head or at the end of the body, add my script tag.
So if you've ever worked with script tags, you'll be pretty familiar with the following.
We'll simply come in and say script; we can say type is text/javascript. You don't technically have to put
that if you're doing HTML 5 apps, but I'll add it. Source equals, and then I'd point to the path of my
jQuery's; we'll say jquery.js for this example, and then add my script tag.
And that's all you have to do to actually get started with jQuery; it's very, very simple.
The important thing though to understand is again, 1.x is for IE 6 through 8 and the new browsers, 2.x is
only for the modern or new browsers, so keep that in mind when you pick the version of jQuery you'd like to
work with.