In addition to loading jQuery from your own server, you can also load it from a Microsoft, Google, or other
server, and we call these external servers Content Delivery Networks. Now there's actually several benefits
if you want to load your jQuery script from Microsoft, or from Google, or even from the jQuery site.
If you actually go to a site, and let's say you went to say a new site, and they use this URL right here for
Google; well if you go to that site, that script is now cached for that domain. If you then go to another
site that also uses this exact same URL, then the script is already there; it's already cached.
So one of the big benefits of using the CDN is you can get some caching benefits because many of the popular
sites out there, instead of hosting jQuery locally, will grab it off a Microsoft or Google site.
Now there's a couple other benefits too. Microsoft and Google have datacenters all around the world, so if
you're in Australia, odds are you're actually going to be grabbing that jQuery script from a server in
Australia, instead of having to go wherever your server's located to grab that script.
So you can get some speed benefits there. Number two, you also get something called parallelism; browsers
limit the number of simultaneous ACDP calls they can make to a given domain.
So, because this is going to be in a different domain from your actual web server, the browser will allow
this to load in addition to whatever you're loading that's local.
So this provides those kind of big benefits: caching, I call it regionality, or closer relationship to the
data services out there and servers, and then finally the parallelism of the browser actually being able to
load multiple scripts from different domains. Now this is great and at first glance you go, well geeze, how
can I lose? You know, I get those three big benefits, and maybe some others, so why would I not want to do this?
Well, what happens if, due to the network, or maybe even due to the Content Delivery Network, that you can't
get the jQuery script? That would certainly cause a big problem, especially if your app is based on jQuery,
because if it can't load that script, you obviously are not going to be able to get to all the cool jQuery
functionality that we're going to be covering throughout this course. Well, what you can do in that case is
you can provide a fallback, and this is a nice little trick, very simple to do.
You can go out to, in this case Google, and we'll try to grab jQuery, and here we would list a specific
version of it, such as 1.9.1, or 2.0.0. Then what we do is if that loads successfully, the Window object
in the browser will have a new property off of it called jQuery. Now that happens as the jQuery script
actually loads. Now, if the jQuery script can't load, then we're going to have a fallback.
So if the jQuery script loads appropriately, we'll have this jQuery property; otherwise, we'll fall back,
and we're going to do a document.write, and write out a script tag that points to a local copy of jQuery.
Well now we can have the best of both worlds; we can leverage the caching and the regional servers, and
potential parallelism, and stuff like that with the CDN, but for some reason we can't get that CDN script,
we can actually just load it locally. And that's an example of working with Content Delivery Networks, and
it's definitely something that I recommend you look into, especially in Internet type scenarios.
Now if you're on an intranet app, I'd say it really depends; if the users are all local it probably makes
sense actually just to hit a local copy of jQuery off of your server, if you have users distributed all over
the place, maybe around the world for instance for your company, then you might want to look at the CDN; it
just depends on your network requirements, firewall constraints, and things like that.
So that's some information on how we can use the CDN, and how we can have a nice safe fallback to load a
local script if we need it.