Once you've loaded jQuery into a page, either with a local copy, or by calling out to a CDN, you can then
take it up a notch and start to use jQuery of course, and that's, after all, what we're after.
So in this section we're going to talk briefly about a little function jQuery provides, which is very, very
useful, and one that you'll find yourself using a lot called ready.
Now, one of the important things to understand with jQuery is that when it's loaded, the window object, as
mentioned earlier, has a little property on it called jQuery. Now you can use that object directly or you
can use an alias of it, which is simply the dollar. And so notice here, I have $(document), and what we're
doing is passing the document object from the browser into jQuery, and then we're going to call the jQuery
ready function. Now, this doesn't wait until everything's loaded, and what I mean by that is with things
like window onload in JavaScript, it's not called until everything's loaded; images, CSS, and all of those
types of files. With the document ready, it detects once the DOM hierarchy has been loaded, so before all
the images and CSS have been loaded. And that allows you to start manipulating the DOM, and that could
include things like I want to show or hide, or add different things into the DOM; I can do that right when
the DOM's ready; I don't have to wait for all the images to download and things like that.
Now, all we have to do is say $(document), and then notice we're passing that in to this little jQuery
function, so again the dollar here, you're going to see over and over and over throughout the class, and
it's simply an alias for the word jQuery. Now if you prefer to type the word jQuery you could do that too.
Now, myself and many others out there, we just prefer to go with the dollar because it works and saves a
little bit of typing. So we're going to pass the document in that wraps it with a special jQuery wrapper.
Now we can get to jQuery functionality and know when the document is ready.
Now when it is ready, what do you want to do? Well you have to give jQuery your own custom functions, and
notice we have an in line anonymous function here, and this is where you perform the action that you should
be doing. So we could be adding things to the DOM, we could maybe trigger an AJAX call to go get some data
from the server, there's a lot of different things we could do. So let's take a look at the document ready
and how we can use it in a live web page, and see when it's called and compare it to the window onload.
Now that jQuery's available in this simple page here, let's take a look at the difference between window
onload, and the document ready that jQuery provides. So I'm going to add our script tag in, and we'll go
ahead and add our type just to be official here, and then we'll add our closing.
Now what I'm going to do first is kind of the standard JavaScript way to detect a load that you'll see out
there a lot. Now there's multiple ways to do this, but this is what I see a lot of people doing.
So we're going to say window.onload, and we're going to call our own custom function here, and then in this
function we're just going to do a simple alert, just to say hey, the window loaded.
So we'll say alert(‘Window loaded'). Alright, now that's kind of the standard way to do it, so let me save
that, we'll run off to the browser here, refresh, and you can see when the loader was called.
Alright, so nothing real fancy at this point. Well, we can also come in and do it the jQuery way.
So I'm going to come in, in fact, let me just put it after to kind of prove the fact that timing will be
faster when it comes to using jQuery. So because jQuery's already loaded, we could either do this:
jQuery(document), and then we could do our ready; or I can simply replace the keyword jQuery with $.
And in all the demos I'll be doing throughout this course, I'll be using the alias of $; it provides a
little bit of a shortcut, don't have to type as much. So we're going to pass the document into jQuery, so
we're literally invoking a jQuery function here, and it's going to return something called a rapset.
Now you don't really need to know what that is, but we'll be covering that in the next module on Selectors a
little bit more. So we pass in the document, and because this is now a jQuery object, we can now get to the
jQuery ready. Now ready is of course defined up in our script. Now what I'm going to do here is say okay,
when it's ready what do I want to do? Well, just like we did with window onload we need to give it a
function, so we're going to say function, and then we'll go ahead and end our function, and then we need to
end the parenthesis here for our ready, so we'll put that in semicolon, and here, I'm going to say alert,
and we'll say ‘Document loaded' so that we know it's a little bit different from the window load to the
document load. Now really what this is, in fact I'm going to change it, it's really DOM has loaded; so not
all the images have loaded, not all the CSS has loaded, but the DOM, the HTML DOM has loaded, so if we had
div down in here, and multiple spans and tables, that's all ready to go, that's how we know that jQuery
could then be used to manipulate this. Now, another option would be I could just move the script below at
the very bottom of --- right before the closing body tag, then I would know that this stuff would be loaded
first, then the script would execute, and that would be another alternative.
But if you want to put it up in the head like we've done here, then you'll want to use the document ready.
Alright, now let's see which one's going to be called for, so window.onload should be called and do an alert
here, and then document.ready should be called, and it also should do an alert.
So let's go back and refresh, and notice that the DOM loaded was called first, now that is correct, because
it doesn't wait for images and all this other stuff; now you might say, but there are no images; true, but
in a real web page, odds are you have images and style sheets and other things; this is going to be called
as the HTML DOM is loaded, and not wait on all that stuff. Then you can see the actual window is loaded.
Well now we can use jQuery to do some cool things, so I'm going to give a quick segue into what we'll cover
in the next module. So let's say we had an Id down here on a div of "myContent", and inside of here we have
this My jQuery enabled Page!. So what we can start to learn with jQuery is, instead of doing these simple
alerts, I'm just going to comment this one out, we can actually come in and start to manipulate things.
The DOM is loaded, so we can go find things. So I'm going to do our very first selector, and this is going
to be our hello world to get it out of the way early on. And I'm going to say go find myContent.
Now this is called an Id selector, and we're going to cover this officially in the next module, but for now,
this will go in and do the equivalent of a document get element by Id; that's what the hash or the pound
means here. myContent is obviously the Id. Then I want to change the HTML here, so just like with ready
off of a jQuery object, we can also do things such as change the HTML, and I'm just going to say ‘Hello World' here.
So now, once jQuery detects that the DOM is loaded, we'll go find our div with the Id of myContent, and
we're going to change the HTML to Hello World, so let's go ahead and run that, and now, once we run this,
we'll be off and running with our first little jQuery example, and you can see it worked; we get Hello World.
Now, I'll certainly admit that's not very impressive, but we've got to start somewhere.
So in the next module we'll be talking much more about Selectors and not only Id's but classes, and some
more complex Selectors, and that's where you're really going to see the power of jQuery.
But at this point you've now seen how to detect when the DOM was loaded through the document ready, and a
simple example of how we can even manipulate the DOM using jQuery.