Now that you've seen how jQuery can be added into a page and the fundamentals that can be used to get
started with it, let's take a little bit of time to run over to the jQuery documentations site.
Now this is a site that I have bookmarked, and something that I use constantly in my applications, because
I'd love to say I've memorized every single function that's available, but some of them I just don't use
that much; some of them I use every day, so it really depends on the application.
I can tell you that if you want to get good at jQuery, you really do need to spend some time getting good at
the jQuery documentation. By doing that, you're going to really speed up your productivity, and it's going
to be a lot less of a frustrating process. So let's go ahead and head over to jquery.com and take a look at
what we can get to as far as docs go.
In addition to getting the script from jquery.com, you can also get to the API Documentation.
I'd argue this is one of the most important things you need to know about, especially if you're going to be
using jQuery a lot. When I first started jQuery right after it came out, I didn't know a whole lot about
the different functions, and luckily they did have some docs back then, and I spent a lot of time in those,
because I'd come up with some new thing and it felt like I was climbing up a cliff because I had no idea
what to do. Well fortunately, the documentation over the years has gotten better and better, and so let's
just take a quick look at what we can get to and what they provide. So you'll notice here on the left, once
I go to the API docs here, that I have some different categories; so if we want to work with AJAX, which
we'll have a whole module on later in the course, or CSS functions, working with Attributes, some of the
Core functionality, and I can scroll through and get to effects for things like animations and events, and
you can see it kind of goes on and on and on, including DOM manipulation.
Well, a lot of this stuff will be used in applications. Chances are you're probably going to be
manipulating the DOM with jQuery. You're probably going to be making AJAX calls if that's how your
application is set up, and if that's how your server is set up. So, we're going to be covering things like
events and DOM and all of that in this course, and so you can see that we can just scroll through and get to
kind of a vast amount of information, so if we click on Selectors, for instance, which will be the next
module of the course, we can see all the different things related to Selectors.
Now if we go back to, let's say the DOM manipulation, let's say I want to insert something into the DOM,
then you'll notice there's several different methods for doing it; I showed the HTML a little bit earlier
in this module, but we can append things, we can pre-pend things, we can change the text, and what's nice
about these is once you click on it, find the function you need, you'll get a nice little explanation of it;
there's some different options on how you can call these functions, and they'll even tell you when it was
added; which version. So if you're using maybe an older version of jQuery for whatever reason, then you'll
know what version this particular function or property is supported in.
Now if we come on down, what I really like about it is you can get to some info on how to use these
different functions or properties. So in this case, it shows us how we can retrieve HTML content, or if we
come on down, you can see how we can actually update HTML or retrieve and use some other functionality; we
can even run a live demo here.
So there's a lot of great stuff in here for how to retrieve HTML; this now shows us how we can set the value
of HTML, which I demoed a little bit earlier with our Hello World, and we should see down here another
example, and there it is. And you can see that they're actually adding a span into the HTML.
And that's the type of documentation that you'll see for most of the different functions and properties
available in jQuery. Now, there's certainly some that have less docs, and some have a whole bunch, but in
general, this is where you need to go to get started. And it's really going to give you a nice jumpstart if
you learn how to navigate this kind of left hand side here. So definitely, I would recommend get good at
the docs, spend some time in the docs, and it's really going to help your jQuery development process.