In this module you've seen an overview of what jQuery is and what it offers; we know it's a very good cross-
browser JavaScript library; you can go to jquery.com to get it, and there's different versions you can grab
based on which browsers you want to support. Now, once you have jQuery we can add it into the page, and
then I showed how we can use things like document ready to detect when the DOM is loaded, and then we can
manipulate DOM elements like I showed with the jQuery HTML function. The other thing I showed at the end
was the jQuery Documentation, and I want to emphasize again how important it is to at least feel comfortable
navigating through that Documentation to find things, because it'll really speed up and make you a more
productive developer by learning it. So now that we've talked about the fundamentals of jQuery, it's time
to jump in to some more fun with it. In the next module, we're going to talk about jQuery Selectors, and
how we can use Selectors to find DOM elements.