The final thing we're going to talk about pertaining to jQuery selectors is some additional flexibility
when it comes to selecting DOM nodes. There's going to be times where you want to select some nodes based on
the text they contain, or the attribute starts with or ends with or contains different text.
So to this point we've only looked at how can you select tags based on a specific tag name, or how do you select
based on ID or class name. There was a little bit of flexibility when it came to attribute selection, since
you could say select based on this string, but you had to have that whole string, it wasn't starts with or
ends with or those types of things. So let's take a look at a few different features of jQuery when it comes
to selectors that you can apply to your programs. So the first one is the contains.
Now contains allows you to search a given element for specific text.
So in this example, you'll notice that we're going to search for a div, but we don't just want all divs, we
want to select a div where that particular div contains the text Pluralsight somewhere in the text.
It could start it, it could end it, it could be in the middle, it doesn't really matter.
Now it is a case sensitive search, so be aware of that because I've beaten my head against the wall for a few
minutes figuring out that particular point before, but in this example, we have a div, we have Expert Pluralsight
Training /div. Well what that'll do is that would match this particular div.
Now if it's the only div that has the word Pluralsight in it, then that's all that would be returned.
The other divs would simply be ignored because of course they don't contain that text.
So that can be very useful when you need it. Another one that's also very useful, I tend to work a lot with
rows and columns, columnar data in line of business applications, and oftentimes you might want to highlight,
for either highlighting to make it easier to read or for some other purpose, the different rows.
Well you could do a lot of this with CSS, but what if you want conditional highlighting, based on this condition,
highlight the even rows or the odd rows or whatever it may be.
Well, fortunately jQuery provides two really useful features, :odd and :even that can be applied.
Now all rows are 0-based, so you have 0, 2, 4, 6, 8, that would be your even rows, and you have 1, 3, 5, 7, 9
and up, and that would be your odd rows, and simply by saying go find tr and then doing :odd, that will return
the set of odd rows or vice versa, you could do even. Then you could apply styles or change the HTML of those
or whatever it may be to do what your application requires. So I'll show an example of this in the demo in
just a moment. Very, very useful though and something that I find a good technique to know about.
Now the last three things I'm going to talk about are going to be related to attributes, very cool stuff for
selecting text, but there's one final one I want to talk about with regard to elements before we move into
attributes, and that is first-child, last-child, and you can even find children in the middle.
So there may be times when you want to find some spans, but you only want to highlight maybe the first child,
if it's a span, throughout your entire page for whatever reason.
Well you'll notice in this particular example we're using yet another selector that we haven't seen to this
point where we're going to say go find all spans, but we only want to find, we want to filter it down to the
first child. And so if you look into this down here to the bottom, you'll see that we have two divs and each
div has two spans, but what we want to do is just select that first span within each parent.
Now it doesn't have to be just that, it could be a td tag, maybe you have a span inside of several columns and
you want to highlight those as well. What matters though is that we're automatically allowing jQuery to
filter based upon some criteria such as first-child, last-child or there's an eq, an equals to give it a specific
position of the children, and I'll show some of this as we walk through the demos here.
It makes it very easy to work with though to find your children without having to write hardly any JavaScript
code as you can see. So the last three things I want to show you are related to attribute selectors.
So we've already talked about attribute selectors, but everything we talked about, they had to contain a very
specific string. So what I'm going to show you here is that you can select attributes based on attribute
where the attribute starts with or ends with or contains a specific value.
So here's the syntax, you'll do that kind of where clause as I refer to it as, where the attribute starts with.
Now this is the carrot symbol, and if you've done regular expressions before, this'll look pretty familiar.
If you haven't, just use the carrot symbol. So the carrot symbol followed by an equals allows you to do this
starts with. So the example shown here is we want to go find all input where the value of the input starts
with Events. And so if we had these, in this case three buttons, then because these all three start with
Events, this would automatically allow us to go into those and work with them.
It makes it really easy to do what you need to do there. Likewise, we can go in and say hey, I want to find
where it ends with. So instead of using the carrot, you can just go in and do the dollar.
Again, that comes from regular expressions. So now we'll say go find me an input where the value attribute
ends with the word Events. Coming down to here, now it's nice because the World, National, and Local might
dynamically be generated for us, maybe you're using PHP or Pearl or whatever it may be to generate the HTML
and you don't have to worry about what it starts with, you just know it contains, or ends with in this case,
the word Events, very simple. And then I just alluded to the final one, which is you can also go in and say
hey, find me everything that contains the text Events. And to do that, you simply use a star.
And so very similar, you say attribute value, or name of the attribute, star equals the value.
So in this case we want to find all the input where the value attribute contains the text event.
So you'll notice in this example we have World Events, National Events, Local Events, it would find all three
of those and go ahead and return it. So that's an example of using contains outside of attributes with like
divs. We looked at how you can do first-child, last-child, those types of things, and we also saw the odd
and even functionality that's really nice when you have a set of children, and I showed it with trs, but keep
in mind that could be used for all kinds of things, lis in the case of unordered list, and stuff like that.
And then finally we talked about three different flexibility features when it comes to attribute selectors
for starts with, ends with, and contains. So let's take a look at an example of using some of these in a demo
application.