If you've ever needed to select a specific tag out of your page as it loads, then you can do that with
document.getelementsbytagname using regular JavaScript. And that works cross-browser, there's not
really a problem there at all. A little bit long in my opinion, but it still works.
Well, in jQuery you can do the same thing, but it's actually much more compact and I think it's just plain
easier, and that's what we're going to cover in this section.
So here's an example of selecting the paragraph and the anchor tags using a jQuery selector.
So you'll notice that we start with the jQuery object, we put the dollar, we then call into a function, and
we pass in the selector syntax, which in this case is simply the name of the tag or element that you want to call.
Now what this will do is go up into the DOM, it'll look for all the tags that are paragraph or anchor tags,
and return those back. So this one up top here would return a collection of paragraph tags, this one will
return a collection of anchor tags. So very, very simple and definitely more compact than the longer
document.getelementsbytagname. In addition to that, what if we wanted to select not only the paragraph tags,
but also all the anchor tags, but in just one statement, we want to merge those into one collection.
Well we can do that as well, we just simply do a comma separated list of the tag names.
So in this example here, we're going to again start with the jQuery object, call into the function for the
selector, and pass in that we want to select the paragraph, the anchor, and the span tags.
Now it's going to return all of those in one single collection, and then you could loop through those, you
could apply styles, you could do all kinds of stuff once you get that collection back, very simple to work with.
Now, you can even go in and instead of just saying find me all these specific tags, what if you just want to
go in and find specific tr tags that are nested directly within a table tag for instance.
Well, you can combine that as well using the ancestor descendant syntax, which will go in and select the
table tag, and then you'll notice that we put a space, and a space then will separate the descendant that
we'd like to select. So in this example we'd say, go find the table, but specifically don't return the table
tag, just return all of the tr tags that are descendants of that particular ancestor, that particular parent.
So that'll go in it and grab those tr tags and allow you to manipulate the children and go even deeper if you'd like.
So let's take a look at an example of using selectors and show you how easy it is to work with.