Let's take a look at how we can select tag names within our HTML page very easily with jQuery.
So first off I have a really simple page, and this is loaded inside of Visual Studio.
Now I want to emphasize that jQuery works with just plain HMTL, PHP, Ruby on Rails, ASP.NET, Web Forms, MVC,
whatever you may want to use. So, although this is my tool of choice for now, which is Visual Studio, you
can certainly do this in Notepad, you could use Aptana, and there's all kinds of different editors, Eclipse
would work great. So nothing specific to Microsoft or any of the Microsoft technologies, but I will say that
things like ASP.NET MVC play very nicely with jQuery out of the box.
So I have an ASP.NET MVC application in front of us here. And you'll notice in my Scripts folder I have the
jQuery script. I also have the vsdoc script so I get some IntelliSense, and that was covered a little bit in
module 1. So what I'm going to do is come in and we're going to do a real simple selector.
So I've already loaded the script and I have the document ready function all wired up and ready to go, so
when the DOM is loaded we're able to go in and get the tags that we want out of it.
So all we're going to do, is like I showed earlier in the slides, we can come in and simply say I would like
to find all the, for instance, p tags, or let's find that img tag.
And that's going to return a collection of images actually, because there might be more than one of those.
So let's go ahead and just to keep it simple, we'll do an alert on that collection, we'll say what is the length
of it. So let's go ahead and run that now and when it runs we'll hopefully see that we, at this stage, have
one image that pops up, and you can see that works appropriately.
Let's go in and there's also some div tags. So let's change this to divs, we'll change this guy to divs, and
then we'll find all the div tags. Now I happen to have three that are actually in the document, so I have a
div there and then there's two more divs right here. There's one that'll be injected dynamically at runtime
as well, so we should see about four of them that appear once we run this, and you'll see we do get back four divs.
Now at this stage, what do you do once you've selected a tag? Well, in a separate module I'm going to cover
some cool things you can do, but let me show you a few of those as we get going here.
So one of the things we could do is we could actually go and for each div, we might want to go in and change
for instance the style. Now this is a class, but we could also go in and directly influence CSS styles.
So if you've been doing this the custom way with JavaScript, and just out of the box type JavaScript, you'd
probably assume we'd come into the style and we'd go from there, but that's not how it works in jQuery.
In fact, you won't actually see styles show up in the IntelliSense here.
This is a jQuery object that's being returned, so it's actually a DOM object, which represents all the divs
wrapped inside of a jQuery object. Now how do we know that? Well, because this is the jQuery object, this
is a call out to the jQuery function, and that returns us a jQuery, in this case, collection.
So what we could do is we want to change, for instance, the background color of all the divs.
You'll notice currently I have blue and red and that's about it, this top one has nothing.
Well, we can go in and say find all the divs, and you'd probably think, well then you've got to loop through
to apply the styles. Well in jQuery that's one of the nice features, you don't have to.
We could come in and say I'd like to change the CSS, and you'll notice I get some really nice IntelliSense
here, and I want to change the property called background-color, and I'd like to change it to, let's just say
green to make it really obvious. That's all I'd have to do. If we find four divs, three divs, whatever it is,
it's going to automatically iterate through those, go in, and apply this style onto each of those divs.
Now it's actually going to influence the style attribute that you would normally type down in the HTML.
So when it gets done, it's like we did this. It would be something like that, but it'd be up in memory because
we're doing it with the DOM. So that'd be the basic syntax, and you'll notice how simple that is.
No looping, very compact, very easy to use. So let's go ahead and run that and we'll see what we have here.
Now it doesn't look phenomenal, but you'll see that that was one div, here was our second div, and then here
was our third div, and you'll see it changed those to green and you can see how easy it was to not only find
the divs, but to also do some work on those divs. And we'll have a lot more I'll be covering in later modules
about how to work with the data once you get it. Now one more I want to show you real quick though, is what
if we wanted to see the HTML inside of the divs, or maybe we want to change the HTML inside of the divs.
Well again, normally what most people would do is they'd come in and make the collection, and then they'd do
something like a for loop or they do the for, and we can do the loop, start at 0 and loop through each div.
Well, much, much easier to do in jQuery. So I'm going to go ahead and start from scratch so we'll do our selector.
Now I'm going to say for each item that's returned, call a function and do something in the function.
And I'm going to keep it real simple since we're not really dealing a lot right now with these functions, I
just want to show you a couple of them. And I'm going to do an alert on the div's HTML so that we can see the HTML
inside of that div. Now, as it loops through each item, it's going to pass you that item.
And the way we can get to it is you do a jQuery wrapper around this.
Now this represents the item you're looping through. So we would say this.html to do it the jQuery way.
Now if you've ever done the innerHTML before using traditional raw JavaScript, then that type of stuff can be
done, but in this case we'd actually have to go this way. So if I run this, what'll happen is as we iterate
through each div, it's now going to pop up, so this represents the table in the upper left, here's the Blue
div, that's the contents, here's the red div you can see, and then there's a hidden one that's inside of here
that is written out for us. And there we go. So, there's many, many things we can do once you do the selector
on a tag, you could apply styles, you could change class names, you can iterate through each one, you can
toggle them, and there's a lot more we're going to cover in the upcoming modules, but that's one of the first
things I wanted to show you. So this particular syntax with the selector works with anything you want.
You can find p tags, you can do all that kind of stuff, but we can also do more as I mentioned earlier.
If we want to find, I don't have any anchors, but let's say we want to find the div and the span tags.
And let's see how many, we had four divs we know, and we should have I believe two spans in here.
So we'll probably get around 6 total items back if we do it this way.
So let's do an alert on the collection and so we'll say collection.length, and it should be in the ballpark
of about six. We'll see what we get, there might be one I missed, but yeah, there we go, so we get six.
So we get the three divs here plus the kind of hidden one, plus inside of each of these two colored divs we
have a span tag, and that's how we can get those. So you can see it's very, very easy to select all kinds of tags.
Now what's cool about this, the same exact technique that I showed you earlier.
If we wanted to say change the CSS of some property, we could say propName, value, and that would now not
only change the propName on just the divs, but it would also iterate through all those span tags.
So, very, very compact, very easy to work with. So that's an example of using tag selectors, or element
selectors, whatever you'd like to call them to select specific tags in the DOM that your webpage has.