The fastest type of selector you can do with jQuery is what's called an ID selector.
Oftentimes in your HTML page you'll go in and you'll give IDs, identifiers, to your specific tags to make it
easy to find, and that's pretty common, been around for a long, long time.
And normally you'd use document.getelementbyid to find those specific IDs.
Well, in jQuery it's even more compact than that. What we can do is we'll, just like we learned with the tag
selectors in the previous exercise in the previous part, you come in and use the jQuery object, so the dollar,
call into the selector function, and you put the name of your ID.
So what we have here down at the bottom is we have a paragraph tag with an id of myID, but if we just put myID
in here as we just learned, it would look for a myID tag, and that's obviously not what we want, we want to
select it based upon the ID. So what this will do is if you put the hash, or the numeric-type symbol, then
it'll automatically go in and know to look for something that's an ID, and that's kind of jQuery's way of
knowing that you don't just want to tag, you want a specific ID, and you've got to remember, especially if
you're new to this, to put that in front or it's not going to work right.
So let's take a look at an example of using an ID selector and how easy it is to work with those.