So back in Visual Studio, I have my document ready function and you'll notice if I scroll on down that we
have a couple different tags in here, we have a form tag with an ID, and that's about it, we don't have a whole
lot going on as far as IDs right now. So let's go ahead and add in just right here at the top, let's go ahead
and add in a div since forms aren't real exciting at this point, and we'll just call this TestDiv.
And inside of that we might have, This is my div text. So if we want to find that particular div, TestDiv,
all we'd have to do is once we know the DOM is loaded, we can come on in, we'll start with our jQuery selector,
and we have to do the pound, or the hash, and do the name of it, TestDiv.
And then we can come in and let's say we want to, well let's grab the HTML and we'll actually write that to
an alert. So HTML again is a jQuery function, and we'll just update that in an alert box.
So let's pop that up and you'll see This is my div text, you can see that it found it.
Now this is by far the fastest way if you're going to be using selectors in jQuery, it's by far the fastest
way to find your different DOM elements. If I do something like we did in the previous module, or section I
should say, and just do a p tag, well that's going to scan the entire DOM and find all of the paragraph tags.
So, by doing the ID, it knows exactly what to look for and it's optimized in the document object model to be
able to find that. So that's all you have to do to find those particular items.
We could come down to wrap up this section and come to form1, put that in there, and that should return for
the form all this table HTML. So let's go ahead and run that, and you can see it did.
We have some stuff that was injected, but here is our table tag that was added into the DOM, which represents
our form down here. So that's how easy it is to use ID selectors.
The nice thing is, as shown in the previous section, in addition again, the HTML, I could certainly modify
styles, I could change classes, I could even add children if I wanted, all programatically and it's very,
very compact, and I just think it's a lot more easy to work with, it's a lot easier to work with I should say
than getElementById, and then we put in TestDiv, which is the traditional way to do it.
So, kind of take your pick there, but you get a lot of benefits by getting the jQuery object instead.