The next type of jQuery selector we're going to look at is the class name selector.
It's very similar to the ID selector, but a little bit different character syntax.
So to use the class name selector, you're actually going to use the period character inside of your selector name.
So for example, we have the jQuery object you can see here, we call into the selector function, and instead
of putting the pound or the hash, whatever you want to call that symbol, we're going to put the period.
Now this says to jQuery, go find any element in the DOM that has a class attached to it called myClass.
So that would match up with a paragraph tag, class equals MyClass, it would match up with an anchor tag, class
equals myClass, we're not telling it which type of class. So the downside of this particular approach here
is that it is going to scan the whole DOM, it's going to have to look through all the different objects that
are loaded up in the memory, analyze if they have this specific class name, and then go ahead and return that set.
Now, the upside is it's really convenient, you can see how easy this is.
There is no equivalent way to do this with normal JavaScript. You'd have to do getElementsByTagName or
you'd have to just loop through all for the DOM, loop through every single node, and then check the class
name on it to make this work. So it is very compact, very easy to use.
Now you can also combine this and do things like multiple class name searches.
So in this example, you'll notice that we're just going to do very similar to what we showed earlier with
selecting multiple tag names, but in this example we're going to grab the BlueDiv and the RedDiv, and that
set of items, the set of DOM nodes that matches those class names will automatically be returned.
So this would give you everything that has those class names out of the DOM.
Now the other thing you can do, and this is good for performance in general, is you can go in and if you don't
know the ID, it's always best to go through the ID if you happen to know that, but in this example you'll see
we have an anchor tag, and then we want to find not all anchor tags, but an anchor tag, or multiple, that have
the class myClass on it. So that is definitely way more efficient than just doing .myClass as in the previous
slides, and the reason for that is we don't have to scan the whole DOM.
This particular example will automatically allow us to go in and then we can grab all of these items and
manipulate the classes. So really, really nice, really easy to work with, but I would recommend be smart
about it. Just because jQuery selectors are very concise and very easy to work with doesn't necessarily mean
they're going to give you the best performance in all situations.
So, in this case, not too bad because we're locking it down, but just be aware of that as you're selecting
your different items. So let's take a look at an example of using the class selector with jQuery within our
webpage.