Hi, I'm Dan Wahlin with Pluralsight. And in this module, we're going to talk about how you can interact with
the document object module using jQuery APIs. Now up to this point in the course, you've learned how we can
use selectors to find nodes in the DOM and we've talked about ID selectors and tag selectors, attributes,
classes, and stuff like that, and I've even shown maybe 2 or 3 functions that you can use as you interact
with selectors and get those notes back, but we're going to take it up a notch in this module and talk about
some of the other items, and in some of those that I did cover, we're going to go into a little bit more detail.
So this is a really good module if you want to dynamically influence the DOM, you want to add notes or remove
notes, change styles, switch out classes, all those types of things.
So the agenda that we're going to go over here is first off I'm going to start with the each function.
Now I've already detailed this a little bit and demoed it in the previous module with selectors.
However, there's a little bit more you can do with it, and I want to point that out real quick.
Very, very useful function though. From there, we're going to talk about how to modify properties and
attributes, and what the difference is there, and it's definitely something you need to know the difference
because there's a different syntax you use, a different way you access the object whether you're going
directly to the raw object or if you're going in through a jQuery object, so we'll talk about that.
Then we'll get into what I find extremely useful. I do a lot of line of business applications where we'll
make calls back to the server with AJAX to get our data as JSON, and then we'll update our page, so we might
add notes, we might remove notes, it depends on what the user did of course.
So we'll talk about the different add and remove APIs that are available and it's very, very simple.
If you've used things like document.createElement, you'll know it's quite a bit of code actually if you want
to add a lot of different HTML nodes or elements into the DOM. Well, with jQuery they've really simplified
it and made it super easy to use, so I'll explain that when we get there.
And then finally, we're going to wrap up this module by talking about styles and then we'll talk about classes.
So you've already seen the CSS function a little bit in the Selectors module, but we'll go into a little more
detail there, and then we'll go into some really good details if you're a big fan of CSS, and I hope you are,
then we'll go into how we can add and remove classes, toggle classes, remove specific classes, all classes,
there's all kinds of stuff that's really fun to do to influence how your page looks within the application.
So let's go ahead and jump into the each function and talk about how you can use that in your jQuery apps.