The next topic we'll cover is how we can modify classes. It's one thing to change the styles, but that gets
a little bit messy since we'd have to duplicate those styles maybe across multiple elements.
Oftentimes to follow best practices, we'll want to use CSS classes.
So let's talk about how we can modify classes and do some different things there.
So to jump on in, there's four main methods you can work with classes, and there's some others as well,
but addClass hasClass, removeClass, and toggleClass are ones that you use fairly frequently if you're working
a lot with CSS classes. It makes it super easy to change the DOM, how it looks and feels to the user in the browser.
So addClass pretty much does as it says. You can add a class. If there's no class at all, attribute on that
DOM element, it'll add it. If there already is a class, it's like adding a space between two classes or more.
HasClass simply checks. You can pass in a string with the class name, it'll return true or false if it has
that class. RemoveClass can either remove all classes off of a node or it can go in and remove a single class.
And then toggleClass turns a class on and off based on is it there or isn't it there.
That one's actually really, really useful in a variety of scenarios.
So let's take a look at how we can use some of these.
So the first one up is addClass. Now very, very simple to use.
All you have to do is go in and find your particular DOM elements or element, depending on what your selector
has. And in this case we're going to select all the paragraph tags and we're going to call addClass to each
paragraph and we're going to add classOne. Well, you could also add more than one if you want at the same
time, just do it like you would in HTML. You can go in and add the space in between the classes and it'll do
the same exact thing. So we'd go find all the paragraph tags in the document, we'd call addClass, and then
this will add classOne and classTwo onto those. So really, really easy to work with.
Now sometimes before you add a class, maybe you want to check if it has another class or something associated
with it for whatever reason. Well, what we can do is we can use the hasClass method, or function.
And so this shows in the example of hasClass, and all you do is pass in the class name that you want to check
if it has that class, and in this case we're going to go and say hey, is there any paragraph tag that has the
class styleSpecific, whatever your style is of course would go there, your class.
And then based on if that's true or false, we can then come in and perform some work inside of this little
JavaScript if statement. So it makes it really, really easy to work with.
So, this is useful anytime we want to check if a DOM element loaded up into memory has that class or not, and
then based upon that criteria, you can perform some work.
The next one we can talk about is removing CSS classes. Now, this is very useful actually when maybe the
user is filling out a form, and as they do that, you change the div that wraps it with a background-color.
Then they move out of that, they lose focus, and move to some other part of the page and you want to change
that background color so it's not highlighted anymore, you want to totally remove the class.
Well, that's super easy to do with removeClass and addClass. So the paragraph tag in this example is going
to be found, all of them, and then we're going to call removeClass, and because we're giving it specific classes
to move classOne, classTwo, classThree, whatever it is, or just one class, it'll automatically remove just
those classes that are available. Now if you just want to remove all the classes, you want to strip everything
off, it's like stripping down the walls when you're painting, you want to take everything off and get it back
to the base, then you could just call removeClass and pass nothing.
JQuery will automatically go in, find all the paragraph tags in the documents, and strip off all the CSS
classes from those. And you can see how productive that is. It's pretty amazing, especially if you've been
doing it the old way, which is you'd have to go do document.getElementsByTagName, then loop through all
the p tags and clear out the class attribute. We don't even have to access the attribute, it just does it for us.
Very, very easy to work with. So these three up to this point, addClass, hasClass, and removeClass are
really nice, but there's one more that's also extremely useful with things like hovering over items, and
that's called toggleClass. So there may be times when you want to add a class, but when it's not there and
you call this code, you want it to remove the class, you want to toggle it on and off like a light switch, it's
on, it's off. What toggleClass does is in this example, if we have a CSS class called highlight, and it sets
the background-color to yellow, then if we want to apply that class selectively based on if it's there, take
it off. If it's not there, add it, then all we have to do is call the toggleClass API.
So in this example we're going to do an ID selector, go find some ID of PhoneDetails, and then we're going to
say toggleClass highlight. So if we run this code and highlight is currently on the PhoneDetails object,
then it's going to remove it. If we run this code and there's nothing on that particular item, then it's
going to add it, so that's why it's called toggleClass. So whereas you could use addClass with removeClass
and hasClass, you could write some if statements and do this code yourself, toggleClass is a heck of a lot
easier because if it's there it removes it, if it's not there it adds it and you don't have to write the if
statements to take care of that. So let's take a look at a demo of how you can use these four different methods
within your jQuery apps.