So let's take a look at an example of how easy it is to work with the four class-specific methods for CSS, so
addClass, removeClass, hasClass, toggleClass. So I have some textboxes, input, type equals text, and let's
say first off that we'd like to add a highlight class onto those when the page first loads.
So we can come back up top, and you'll notice that I have a highlight class already created for us that just
sets the background-color to yellow. Well, what I'd like to do is let's go find all the inputs that are type
text, so we can do that with a selector, so let's go ahead and we'll say Class functions.
And we'll go in and say input type equals text, and that'll find all the textboxes for us with our selector,
and then we can say addClass and we can give it the class Highlight.
And that's all we have to do to take care of that. So we can go in, we can run this, and once it gets to that code
you'll see that it automatically highlights both of those and takes care of that for us.
I'm going to take out that alert real quick. And likewise maybe we want to remove.
Well, let's go down and let's see what we have here for an ID. We have LastNameTextBox for the ID of this guy.
So, likewise we can come in, we can do, in this case an ID selector, removeClass, and then we can give it Highlight.
Now because there's, I believe only one class on here at this point, we could just leave highlight out and it
would still work, but let's go ahead and run it as is and you can see now we just have this guy highlighted.
Very nice. Now just to prove the point, let's go ahead and just to remove class and you'll see the same result,
but it'll strip off all classes. So if we had RedDiv or BlueDiv plus the Highlight applied, it would strip
off everything together. I'll go ahead and put that back for now.
Now you obviously probably wouldn't even want to do this, why highlight it in the first place if you don't
need it. So, what we could do is we could do the hasClass. So we could do LastNameTextBox hasClass Highlight,
and we can wrap an if statement around that, and then we could change it based on some condition.
Now I'm not going to do that, I'm going to do a little different scenario.
So I want to make it so that first off we don't highlight it right off the bat.
So I'm going to leave those as comments, but we don't want to highlight that.
Instead what we want to do is when that textbox gets focus, we want to go ahead and set it to yellow with jQuery
or unset it, remove that class. Now again, I could combine addClass, removeClass, and hasClass with all
this, but toggleClass is really what this is geared towards. So we haven't gone into how to handle jQuery
events yet, so I'm going to handle it the traditional way and put it right into the HTML, but keep in mind
that we can certainly do this a different way and that'll be coming up in a different module.
So I'm going to say onfocus, let's call the Focus function and we'll just pass this particular item, and then
we'll also call onblur and we'll call Blur and we'll pass in this and let's put that on both of these textboxes.
So we have our onfocus and our onblur, and they're going to call the Focus and the Blur and pass themselves
into that. Now again, this is the traditional way to do it. There's some other ways you can do this, I'm going
to show you in a later module. So let's go ahead and make those functions inside of our script block.
So we'll make a Focus, we'll just call textbox, and let's do a Blur.
Now this is going to, when we call this, it's actually going to pass in the DOM object, so we're going to go
ahead and wrap that. And we're going to do toggleClass, Highlight, and then when Blur is called, we're going
to toggleClass Highlight. Now what that's going to do, and we could, I'm going to change this up to wrap up,
but we could just call the same one, we could call, I don't know, FocusBlur or something, but what we'll do
is now when they focus, if Highlight is not on that textbox that's passed in, we're going to set it, or vice
versa, if they Blur and we call toggleClass Highlight now should be on it, because this would have been
called first, and we're going to remove it. So let's go ahead and try that out.
So we'll focus, you can see it sets it, we'll change, and you can see it removes it.
Really, really nice, and makes it super, super easy to work with.
Now obviously there's some other CSS tricks you could do to work with this type of same scenario, but there's
a lot more you can do because now we have full JavaScript. Now let's just go ahead and change this to FocusBlur,
and we'll just use the same exact item here, same function, and so we'll set this to FocusBlur, FocusBlur,
because now, we really just need the same exact function called, because if it's there, it's going to remove
it, if it's not there, it's going to add it. So we're going to be able to reuse our code a little bit better,
refactor it. So we'll go ahead and run it, we'll focus, and you can see we get the same result.
Really easy to work with. So obviously you can make yours look a heck of a lot better than what I have going
here, the goal of what I'm showing in this lovely screen is mainly just to focus on the concepts, but you
could certainly take it up to the next level and make it look really nice for your particular forms.
But that's an example of using addClass, removeClass, we could do hasClass, and then toggleClass.
It really simplifies what we'd have to do otherwise and I like the fact that we can still leverage traditional
JavaScript where we pass in the DOM object, then we put that in a jQuery wrapper so that we can access the
jQuery APIs. It makes it super easy to work with. So that's an example of how you can work with classes using
jQuery syntax.