In this module, we've seen how we can iterate through nodes and modify the DOM in a lot of different ways.
So we started off by talking about the each function and I talked about how you can, as you're iterating through
the nodes with each, get to the index value and how we can take the raw DOM objects that were fed and wrap
those with a jQuery wrapper to do all kinds of other things. I also threw in a couple tips and tricks there
for performance that I would definitely recommend you take a look at and consider as you use that each method.
We also talked about how you can modify properties and attributes.
We talked about how if you have a raw DOM object you can get to the properties of that object directly versus
if you have a jQuery object you can use the attr function to modify the attributes of that particular element
from the DOM. From there we moved on to modifying the DOM using append or prepend functions.
Very easy way to do it, definitely simplifies things as compared to using document.createElement, but keep in
mind, you can still use the traditional ways of interacting with the DOM, it's just in most cases jQuery is
going to make it easier for you. From there we talked about the wrap function and how we can wrap different
children with a parent. It makes it really nice if you want to change for instance the styles or classes
associated with that group of items. And we talked about how we can change styles and work with classes and
even toggle classes on and off, it makes it really easy to do that as well.
So a lot of good stuff in this chapter, and I hope that'll help jumpstart your jQuery development and your
projects.