jQuery provides an easy way to interact with DOM objects directly, or using jQuery object wrappers, and we're
going to talk about both of those. We're first going to talk about how we can modify DOM object properties
directly, then we're going to go into how we can take a jQuery wrapper, a jQuery object, and call into the
jQuery APIs to do other things. So two different scenarios, but they ultimately end up doing a very similar
purpose, similar task. So the first thing we're going to talk about is we just covered the each function in
the previous section and I talked about how as we loop through using the each, that function that gets called
will pass in the index, and then we also get passed the raw object.
Now you can get to it if you don't pass it as a parameter using this.
Now if you just use the keyword this, then it represents the raw DOM object, and then we can get to the direct
properties of that object just by using the dot syntax, so .title in this example.
And then we're going to assign the title to a value of My Index equals, and then the index that was passed in.
So because this represents the raw DOM object, we don't have access to the jQuery API at this point.
Now we could, as I showed earlier in the selector areas of the course, we could go in and put dollar parentheses
around this, and that would allow us to go ahead and use that as a jQuery object, but then you wouldn't have
direct access to the properties like this because now it would think it's not a raw DOM object, it's actually
a jQuery object. So the big thing to know, and here's kinda how I think of it is if you're using a tool that
gives you IntelliSense or code help, Aptana, their tools, or Visual Studio or others, then if you do this dot
and you don't see any of the jQuery API functions showing up, you're probably on the raw DOM object, and
that's why you're not seeing those. So if you want to convert that into a jQuery object so you can do something
else with it, then you'd have to wrap it with the dollar parentheses and use a selector type syntax.
So that's an example of how we can modify properties using just the raw DOM object itself.
Now we can also use jQuery though to go in and modify what we're going to call attributes of the object directly
as well. Now the way that works is once you've found one or more objects, and this works not only on a single
one like this ID selector, but even on a collection, which I'll show you in a moment, then you could come in
and in this example we're going to say let's go find CustomerDiv, and we want to grab the title attribute of
that particular element. So if you think of the HTML, the HTML might have a title attribute on the div and
we want to go ahead and grab that. Now that's very similar in this case to the title property, but dollar
CustomerDiv gives us a jQuery object. That's why we can then do .attr title.
So a lot of people call this the attr function, very, very useful, something I use a lot in my jQuery apps
because oftentimes I want to manipulate those attributes based on what's occurring with the end user.
So in this example we'll simply select that div, and then we're going to grab the title and we're going to
store it in a value. Now of course there's a lot of times where you just don't want to grab it and select it,
you actually want to update it. So the attr function also takes the attribute name and the value if you'd
like to set a value. Now this one provides kind of an interesting thing that jQuery does.
We've talked about the each function and how I could say dollar img, do a tag selector and then do the each
and loop through each one, then we could change the title as I just showed earlier using the raw DOM object.
Well, with jQuery, once you've selected a collection or a set of DOM objects, now it's going to internally
have a wrapper around those. And so if you do .attr title My Image Title, it would actually update the title
attribute of each image within your page. Now obviously you may not want to do that depending on what it is
you have going, but I find it pretty cool that it does that because I don't even have to loop through it, jQuery
just magically, based on the fact that this might return more than one image, will automatically update the
title attribute of each of those images, I don't even have to do an each loop, that's pretty cool.
Now it also gets even better though. What if we don't want to just update title while we're looping through,
while jQuery I should say, loops through each of the images, we might want to update title, maybe the style
or something else. Well we can do that as well using what's called JSON, JavaScript Object Notation.
Now I'm going to talk about that in just a sec, but let me show you a simple example to start.
So we have the similar scenario as the previous one where we have a selector on image, but we're not going to
change just a single attribute, jQuery supports doing what's called a map, and a map is basically just a JSON
object, it's an object with properties. Now those properties need to map up, or match up, either way you
want to look at it, to the images properties, or attributes in this case.
So we already talked about title. Now in this case, title:, this is a separator between the value of the
property and, well I'm sorry, the name of the property and the value of the property.
Then notice we put comma, style:, and then the value of the style that we want to set here.
Now, that is all wrapped with these brackets, so the start of this little object, this JSON object, is here,
and it ends down here with this bracket, and it has two properties.
So what this'll do is jQuery will now find all the images, it'll go in, iterate through those for you, and
then set the title and the style to these appropriate values. Now style can be said, as I showed in the selector,
through the CSS property, and that's normally how I would do it, but this is just demonstrating that you can
assign multiple attributes in one shot, very good for performance because I don't have to iterate through all
of the images twice just because I want to set two, three, four, whatever it is attributes I want to set,
very useful. Alright, let's talk about JSON just a little bit more and show you another example.
This is going to come up again in AJAX, so if you've never done this before and never seen JSON, you might
say hey, wait a sec, what's this JSON thing you're talking about.
Well, JSON is just a way to delimit objects and to find properties and values.
It's been around actually since the late 90s in almost all the major browsers.
It's a feature of the JavaScript language, it really wasn't leveraged until several years ago, but it wasn't
leveraged until fairly recently. And, this is something that you just saw an example of that with the title
and the style attribute, but here's just more of a data JSON object.
The start of the object is here and it ends here. Now a JSON object doesn't have a name typically, it's an
anonymous object. Now you'll see in a moment that depends, but FirstName is the property name, John in the
value, comma, LastName Doe. And you'll notice, so properties and values again are separated by a colon, a
comma separates the different properties from each other. So if you've done XML before, you would normally
wrap a tag around John, you'd have a start tag and an end tag around John.
Well JSON is just a more compact way of kind of describing data, it's very, very easy to work with actually,
it's something I use a lot, especially when you get into AJAX functionality.
So, you'll notice we have FirstName and LastName. Well we also have a nested JSON object, and this case the
property is named Address, but Address isn't just a simple value, it's actually a nested JSON object.
So you'll notice that it starts with the red bracket here and then we have the closing down here.
And then that object has its own set of properties. So the object officially doesn't have a name, but that
object is assigned to a property of this parent object, and that property is called address.
So that's kind of how it works, you can nest them, and you can even do a raise with JSON.
You do that by doing the square brackets, which isn't shown here, but you can definitely do it when you do
AJAX to pass back multiple customers as in this example. So that's what JSON is in a nutshell, and going
back, that's exactly what's going on right here with the attr function, we're simply passing a JSON object,
it has two properties, and then once we select that image, it'll update both of those attributes on that object
for us. It makes it very, very easy to work with. So, let's take a look at using raw property modifications
versus JSON objects and jQuery objects to use the attr function.