Now that you've seen the direct properties that can be set and the attr function that jQuery provides, let's
see it for real in an example here. So if we come on back down to the divs I was working with in the previous
demonstration with the each, we have two divs, and let's say that we'd like to first go in and set the title
of these divs. Well, if we're just looping through those in general and doing something like the following,
then we're going to get the raw object back, and when I say raw, I mean the raw DOM object.
So if we do this.title equals Some title, this is what's passed when the function is called as it loops through,
in this case we're going to get back two items that are going to be passed in.
And so we can just take that raw DOM object and we can update it directly.
So if we run that and then mouse over the divs, we should see title Some title applied.
So let's go ahead and run that first, and then we'll come back and show how to use the attr function.
So let's mouse over it and you'll see some title shows up as you would expect.
So you see we're able to actually update the title directly. Now, we could also go in as we loop through and
we can get to that title as well of course, and obviously it's going to return the same value because we just
set it, but there we go, Some title and Some title. And that would be the raw DOM object way to do this.
And you can change all kinds of properties using this if you'd like.
Now you can also though come in and wrap this into a jQuery object.
So we could say this., and now notice in IntelliSense here in Visual Studio, we have full access to the jQuery
API, and so therefore we can come in and do some of the cool stuff, there's our attr function, the attr function.
So we can come in and we can override, let's go ahead and try to override that with Some title 2, just so we
can distinguish, but we need to tell it which property of course, we can't just give it the value.
So we're going to say title, Some title 2, and then we'll end it, and then let's run it and see what we get here.
So we'll mouse over those and you'll notice it now overrode it.
So what I wanted to demonstrate here, and the reason I kind of did the same thing twice, is ultimately this
is updating the same property that this is updating, it's just that because this is the raw DOM object, we
can go directly to that property versus if we come into the jQuery object, now we have to go and get into the
jQuery API to do it. Now a lot of the time I just prefer to use the attr function, but to each their own.
It depends on who you talk to there, but that's kind of how that works.
So we'll go ahead and leave those there. Now moving on down, we can also go in and let's say that we want to
change, right now there's a background-color and there's no font though, you can see the styles of each of
those divs are defined here, but let's say we want to go in and change those to something else, but I don't
want to use an each. Say we want to change the font on them. Well, we can go in and the best way to do this
would be to use CSS to find it, then we could come in and say font-size, let's go something kind of big here,
we'll just do a 20pt real quick. And the CSS property will update the style and you can see that worked, we
now have 20 point fonts. Well, you can change anything you want on these though.
Instead of doing it this way, I'm going to assume we want to change several properties, or attributes in this
case. So I'm going to use the attr, we're going to wrap that down to there, and then inside of it I'm going
to pass what jQuery calls a map. And this is my JSON object. In fact, let me go ahead and just wrap this so
you can see it down in here a little bit easier. And now we can come in and we can simply say the name of the property
we want to change, so we'll go ahead and put a colon to separate it, and then we'll put the value.
So I'm going to put Some title 3 since up here we'd have Some title, but it'll be overridden by Some title 2,
now we have Some title 3, and now I can't use CSS:, that's a jQuery function, but I can do style and we could
do font-size, let me do it all out here, and we'll do, let's do like 14pt.
And then, we could even chang the background-color if we wanted, background-color is yellow to distinguish
easily. And we could just keep putting commas and we can change all kinds of things on these divs if we wanted.
So that's an example of we're able to actually find the target divs in this case and automatically apply two
attribute values, or two properties really, to those, and then pass those into this attr function and work
with it. So let's go ahead and run it and we should see a 14pt font, we should see yellow, and we should see
Some title 3 passed into that particular value.
And there we go, not real easy to read, but we'll mouse over it, there's Some title 3, and we could even come
in and on that style say color Black, run it again, and we could do this.
Now, I mentioned earlier that you could do the style this way, and absolutely that's fine, but let me show
you something called chaining that ties into this. Now that we've talked about some of the APIs a little bit
more, jQuery has a very cool feature called chaining that could be used.
And so to be honest, what I just did is going to have less code involved, but let's say we had multiple properties
we want to add, and then as I'm looping through each of these, I don't want to just change the attributes, I
also want to change their style, but I would prefer to do it, we're going to say, through the CSS function.
So what I typically like to do here is I'll wrap these and I like to wrap each one on its own line if it gets
too long, because otherwise if it gets strung out all the way over to here, it gets a little bit hard to read
and so I'll come in and do whatever I need to do to make it look nicer, but this is chaining.
Now what attr does is it's going to still return the modified set of objects that were selected with this
tag class selector. So literally I'm going to tag on, in essence I'm putting this function after this function,
right there, then we're going to call another function. And we can do CSS and we could say background-color,
yellow. And then, if I want to do CSS again, and again I'm going to wrap it to keep it a little bit easier
to read, then we could just keep chaining these. So we could say color, black, .css, and we could say font-size,
20pt, and we could just keep going to town. Now I'm done. So we just chained one, two, three, four functions
together. Now you may look at this and say I prefer setting the style up here, and that's fine, whichever
way you prefer is good with me, but the bottom line here is that jQuery allows you to chain different functions
together to, instead of having to iterate through these and just change the attributes and then iterate
through them again and change this, and then iterate through them again and change this, that would get
expensive. Well this allows me to do it all in one shot. So it's only selecting these two divs from the DOM
once, then it's allowing me to act upon those particular nodes, so if we run it, we won't see much of a change
here, but you can see we get to Some title 3, the font's been applied, the background has been applied, yellow,
and the color of the font has been applied to black here in this example.
So that's object chaining combined with using the attr function, and like I said, you can certainly, if you
prefer to do style, that to me is actually a little bit easier than doing all this code, but it depends on
what you're doing. Some of these values might dynamically come in and who knows what you're doing in your app.
So that's an example of setting raw properties using the attr function, using the attr function with a map,
and doing jQuery chaining in this particular demo, so some really, really useful stuff you can do in your
jQuery applications.