Changing object properties and attributes is important, but there's going to be times when you want to add or
remove specific nodes from the document object module. So in this section of the module, we're going to talk
about how you can do that with jQuery, and we're going to talk about four main methods that you see here.
So there's some other things you can do and different techniques, in fact I even showed in the previous
example of how you could use the HTML function to actually add in stuff on the fly, but the kind of official
way to work with the DOM is the append, appendTo, prepend, and prependTo.
Now I'm only a big fan of two of these, which is append and prepend, but I'm going to show you how all four
can be used, although I don't really use two of those a whole lot.
Now you can also remove nodes from a given element by using the remove function as well.
So very simple to do, you can either go to that object directly or you can remove groups of objects doing a
more generic selector to find those different nodes in the DOM.
So append will append a child to the bottom of the existing children versus prepend will put it at the beginning
of the children. And like I said, we're going to look at all four of those and see how you can use them.
So let's talk about appending two nodes first. There's oftentimes the scenario where you might have a
container like a div, and inside of that div you might have some different children you want to add as the
data changes, and this is very useful as you get more into more robust applications with AJAX integration,
where again you go out to the server, you get back some data, and then you want to take that data and update
it up into the document object model, the DOM. Well there's two main ways you can append nodes to a particular
item. Now like I said, one of these I don't really use a whole lot, the other I do.
The first one is the appendTo, and it works great. I don't find myself using this one as much, but I know other
people that love it, so it just depends. But what you do is you simply give it the string of HTML that you'd
like to add up into the DOM. Now you'll notice I'm not having to call document.createElement anywhere in here.
It really saves you a lot of time compared to the normal JavaScript way of doing this where you have to go
through the document object. Now obviously behind the scenes jQuery is interacting with the document object,
but it just saves us that time. So in this first one, we have a span with office in parentheses and the closing
span tag, and we want to append that to all matches, all nodes, that have the officePhone class on them.
So this would go find everything that has officePhone on it as a class, and it would append this span at the
bottom of the child collection. Now I actually prefer to do the selector first, and again it just depends on
the scenario, it's not that one's better than the other, but I find myself using the bottom one, the append
a little bit more. So I'll come in and say let's go find all the nodes that have the officePhone class and I
would like to append this particular span, which is obviously the same thing, at the bottom of the child
collection. Now, that's just awesome. If you've been doing this the old fashioned way, you could see how
much time this can save you because you can add in whatever HTML you want in here, you can build up that string,
and as I showed in the each demo earlier in this module, you would want to build up your string first before
you call the append method because you want to interact with the DOM the least amount possible, keep your
interaction down to a minimum. So that's one way that you can append nodes, or two ways I should say, you
can append nodes. Now you might not want to put the nodes down at the bottom though, you might on the append
want to put them up top of the child collection. And that's where the prepend comes into play.
So you can prepend using prependTo, or you can use prepend, and it's the exact same functionality as the
append that we just covered. So you take that string, and then you can do prependTo and you can find what it
is you want to grab, or you could first do my preference, which is let's find what we want to append, or prepend
in this case, call the prepend method, and then give it that particular string.
So regardless of which way you choose on the append or the prepend, very, very easy, super, super productive
when it comes to really dynamic apps where you have to get that data up into your page, the DOM.
Now you can also go in and you can do a really cool feature called wrap.
And this is useful if you have maybe a set of objects or just one object maybe, but you want to wrap all those
with a parent. Where this comes into play oftentimes is you might want to highlight a set of items, and maybe
you want to change the CSS class or styles that are being used, but you don't want to individually do it on
the items, you want the parent for instance to drive say the background-color, or something like that, or the
border. So in this example, if we had a div with class state, and then we have this text inside of it, if we
want to wrap that with another div that has a class called US_State.
So notice that we have a div here, class is US_State, but we just close it, shortcut close.
And you could do it either way, the long tag way or the shortcut.
Well, what this does is this will actually wrap this div around this div.
So what makes it really easy to apply this US_State class as maybe the background or whatever you're doing as
far as the CSS goes to change this, so this is what you'd end up with down here, down in the bottom.
So we'd go find all the states, we would then wrap all those with this particular div, and that'll just add
it as a wrapper just like you see. So again, very, very performant, it's a super productive feature if you're
working with a lot of DOM manipulation and you need that particular functionality.
So in addition to appending, prepending, and wrapping nodes, you can also go in and remove nodes as well.
So we can go in and use a remove method, very simple to do. So the remove method is actually very functional.
You can remove specific items or you can even just remove more, I guess narrow-focused type items.
So what this will do is the remove will come in and remove all matched elements.
So what I meant by more specific or least specific is in this example we're being kind of general, we have a
phone class and a location class and we have that comma so that we can define both those sets of nodes.
So who knows, that might return 50 nodes potentially. Well, if you want to remove every node that has those
classes associated with them, one or the other, then you just call remove, and that's it.
It's very simple versus with the document object model, you first have to find the node, then you have to
find the parent, then you have to remove it off of that parent, and it's actually quite a bit more tricky.
This makes it super, super easy, and of course, if you only have one specific node you want to remove, then
you could just use an ID selector with the hash or the pound, and remove that node very, very easily.
So it's again, a very productive thing. And I think of anything we're going to talk about in jQuery in this
course other than selectors, which will definitely up your productivity, I think the append, the prepend, wrap,
and remove features are extremely powerful for situations where you have some really dynamic pages, especially
in AJAX scenarios where you're getting data from the server. So now that we've talked about some of those,
let's look at an example of some of those in action and see how it works.