The jQuery DOM manipulation APIs are really easy to use, so let's take a look at how we can use append, prepend,
and some of the others that we just discussed. So first up, I have a div, and this particular div is
TableContainerDiv, and right now that's all it has is a table, but let's say that above the table, and maybe
even below the table, we would like to put in some extra nodes.
Well, if we did this the traditional JavaScript way, I'd have to come in and say var child1 equals
document.createElement, and then we'd have to create an element.
Let's say that I want to add some divs, so we could do div. Then we'd have to say child1., and we could get to
the attributes or we could set attribute actually, and we could set those or we could go through the attributes
collection, either way. And it'd be quite a few lines of code in order to build that up.
Now you might say well, you could also go in and do document.getElementById, and we could find
TableContainerDiv, and then we could get into the innerHTML and we could manipulate that maybe.
But if we want to add stuff above and below, it'd be a lot of string manipulation going on, plus it just gets long.
Well, with jQuery it's really, really easy to append and prepend different nodes.
So the first thing we'd have to do of course is find the node. So we'll do TableContainerDiv and that'll
find it with an ID selector. The next thing we'll do is we're going to call append.
So I'm going to put something at the bottom, and let's just put in a span, and I'm going to give it a style so
that we can pick it out easily. We'll say background-color is green, and we'll just say Appended Child 1.
Now I'm going to kind of borrow that line. If we want to prepend, really the same thing.
I'll change this to Prepended Child 1, we'll change this to prepend.
And we're off and running, and that's it, you don't have to build up this document.createElement and set the
attribute, it's quite a bit of code to do that, or even really touch the innerHTML property.
What jQuery will do is it'll actually convert this string into a node, handle all the attributes, all that
stuff for you, and then append or prepend as appropriate to your target parent.
So if we run this now, we should see above a span and below a span that's a green background, and there we go.
So we have our prepended child and we have our appended child below it.
So moving on, we could do this the opposite way as well. Now I don't prefer this way nearly as much, but we
could come in and we could give it the string first, so let me cut and paste that, then we could say appendTo
and we could find our TableContainer. Now right off the bat, this is not the most efficient way to do this.
So let me go ahead and fix things up a little bit. What I'm going to do is cache this object because this is
going to select it each time. So we're going to cache that and just say tcd.append, and same thing here to
keep that a little more efficient and it'll be a little more compact as far as coding goes.
And so we'll say append this particular child 2 to that node, and since it's going to be appended, let's add
a br so it looks good. Likewise, we could do the prepend much the same way on this prepend that we just did,
I'm going to add a br. Well actually we'd need to be right there because this will be the second child now.
So we'll go ahead and take that one out. This will now be the first child because we're going to prepend it
to the same parent, this TableContainerDiv down here, and let me change this to Prepended Child 2.
So if we run that, now we should have four green areas, four spans.
There's our Child2, Child1, Child 1 and Child 2, and you can see how that works.
When you append, it always adds it at the bottom, when you prepend, it always adds it at the top.
Very, very easy to work with. Like I said, I prefer this way, but this way is certainly valid as well, so whichever
way you like. Okay, so that's an example of working with those types of things.
Now, some other things we can do with manipulating the DOM is there may be times when you have some children
and you want to wrap those children in a specific parent, because maybe that parent has a different class you
want to apply to change the border or the background, whatever it may be.
So we can come in and use wrap to do that, and the wrap method is really, really easy to work with.
So if we scroll on down, I have three spans right here that just gets written out one after another with a space
in between them, and if we run it, you'll see these spans right there.
So Span 1, Span 2, Span 3. Well, what if I'd like to wrap a div around the spans?
Let's go ahead and do that. So first off, we'd have to know what the spans are.
Now I just have kind of a bogus class of Foo here, so I'm going to grab that.
We'll come back up and we need to go in and find that span with Foo.
So I could of course just put that, but we want to make it as efficient as possible, so we'll do, since it's
on a span tag, we'll do span.Foo. And from here, now I can say hey, I want to wrap that span with a particular
parent. So I can come in and say div, let's go ahead and give it a class of, let's use one I already have up here.
So I have BlueDiv and RedDiv. Let's go ahead and do RedDiv. So the class of that will be RedDiv, and then I'm
going to also add another class, which is just kind of a marker class called ParentWrapper.
And then I would simply end my div that I want to wrap. Now what jQuery will do is it'll automatically go find
the span and then wrap this div around that particular span. Now let's run it and see what happens, and you
can see it works, they're all going down now vertically and it almost looks like there's one single div that's
wrapped around all the spans. Well, that's actually not the case, and to prove that, what we can do is I can
go in, grab this parent wrapper, and let's go find that div. So we'll say div with a ParentWrapper on it, a
CSS class, each. And now what I can do is grab the HTML. So we're going to wrap that this keyword and we'll
call HTML and I'm going to put that up in an alert actually. So we'll say alert the HTML.
Now you're going to see that when it finds these, each one's going to have its own span inside of it, so it's
not wrapping one div around all of the spans, it's wrapping, really there's three divs since we have three spans.
So we'll go ahead and run it, and there we go. So there's the first div, there's the second div for Span 2 over
here, there's the third div that had the class, or has an ID it looks like on it, and we're kind of off and running.
So very easy to work with this and wrap around particular areas.
And it may be not quite as useful for a span because maybe like for instance around this form I want to highlight
based on something, a background-color that they need to fill that out in case there was multiple forms on a
given screen. All kinds of things, the sky is the limit as to what you can do.
Now the other thing you can do that's really nice for DOM manipulation is you can remove nodes.
So we can call the remove API. Let's see here. Well, we could go in and if we wanted to remove all those divs
we just added that have ParentWrapper on them, then we could easily do that.
Now that's going to remove the div, but watch what happens here.
We'll get past these guys, it's still there, and there we go, they're all gone.
So you can see not only does it remove the div, but it also removes all the children of course because now
that child has nowhere to go. So that takes care of doing that really easy, especially compared to the normal
way we do this with the DOM, which is you have to find the node first, then once you find the node you can remove
it from the parent, which means you have to find the parent. It just gets a little bit more painful using
the kind of custom JavaScript way. Everything I've shown you here works cross-browser, it's very, very easy
to work with and as a result, you're more productive, at least I hope you are.
So, that's an example of append, prepend, wrap, and remove. And there's some others you can do.
Again, I'd highly recommend, check out the jQuery documentation, let's run there real quick because I'm going
to show you how to find these. If you go to jquery.com/docs or docs.jquery.com, either way, you can come
down to Manipulation it's called. Well this is all the DOM manipulation APIs.
So there's the appends, we've already talked about attribute, you can do before, you can clone things, we've
talked about CSS, and there's a whole bunch, we won't have time to go into everything, but there's some other
remove type things. You can remove attributes, remove classes, we're going to talk about that next actually.
Replace, so I could actually go find a node and replace it with a different node if I wanted.
So there's all kinds of cool stuff you can do here, including even unwrap, wrap and unwrap.
So I'd highly recommend, get to know all these different APIs because there's even more than we have time to
cover in the video series.
Alright, so no pun intended, but that's a wrap.