There's going to be times when you want to modify the styles of elements in the DOM, so that's very easy to
do and it's actually something we've briefly talked about, but let's officially jump into working with styles.
So, you can jump in and work with the CSS function and it makes it really easy to get the value of a particular
item or set the value of a particular item. So in this case you'll notice that we have a div, and on all the
divs, since it's a tag selector, we're going to go in and say hey, let's change the font color to red so that
any text that's in those divs would automatically have that particular color.
Very, very easy to work with. Now what's nice about the CSS function is it's kind of like the attr function.
You can also go in and you can set multiple values. So we can go in, and in addition to the color, which in
this case would set kind of a light gray, ccc, we could also go in and say let's also change the font-weight
to bold in this case. Well, this is the JSON object that we talked about earlier.
So, we can come in and we can actually pass CSS a JSON object, just like we can the attr function, and this
JSON object starts here, it ends here, and of course it has two properties.
And so you'll notice these properties are quoted, in this particular case you can get away with either
non-quoted or quoted for the properties, but it's a little bit different than we saw before.
So that's really nice though when you'd like to set multiple CSS values.
Now earlier, I ran a demo where I chained multiple CSS, because mainly I wanted to show how you could chain
jQuery functions together. Well, you really don't need to do that, you can just pass the different values
you want as a JSON object and you can be done with it, it makes it much easier to work with.
So let's take a look at how we can work with that in our application.