I've already demoed the CSS function earlier, but I'm going to go ahead and come back up to what we did and
work with that a little bit. So I showed you how we can call .css and pass in the background of yellow, the
color black, but I chained multiple CSS functions together with the attr function.
Now, that certainly works and is fine, but in this case I really wouldn't chain them, I prefer to use a JSON
object. So what I'm going to do is we're going to convert this guy into a JSON object, and then we'll come
in and actually assign these values and we'll use the colon to separate the property name from the property value.
So we'll take out the comma there and we'll do one more right down here, which is going to be our font-size.
Okay, now let me change this up just a little bit and we'll go ahead and have, let's say, purple and white,
not maybe my favorite colors, but we'll go with it. So I'm still going to use chaining, you'll notice that I
have the attr function to set the title property, but then I'm going to chain the result object that's returned
and assign CSS to it, but I'm not just going to do multiple CSS calls, that's kind of wasteful on syntax.
Instead, we're going to come in, and let me just wrap this down to make it really easy to read, we're going
to define a JSON object start and end, and then we're going to define three properties, separate those with
commas. So if we run this, we'll now see that we get the same effect, but we have purple here, and there's
our div and the names don't really match anymore, but you can see the idea there.
In fact, just to demonstrate chaining, we could come in and we could chain this and say text equals Changed Color.
So we're going to chain three methods together now, three functions, and we'll get through the alert from a
previous demo and there we go, we have Changed Color. So chaining is really nice, but the point of this demo
is that although you could chain multiple CSS functions together, it's a lot easier generally, and I think
it's easier to read because they're all in one place and it's easier to maintain as a result, but you can
just do that directly using the CSS function and a JSON object.
It makes it really, really nice to work with.