AJAX is one of the most important features introduced into browsers over the past 10 years, in my opinion.
It allows us as developers to integrate a variety of data into our applications and make it so we don't have
to reload the page every time a user clicks on something or blinks for the most part.
And so in this module, we're going to talk about the AJAX features available in jQuery, how we can use those
to get data from a server and integrate it back into our page using some of the features we've already talked
about in jQuery. And we've talked about how to manipulate the DOM and how to handle events and use selectors
to find DOM elements. So we're going to tie all that together and start working with some data that we're
going to retrieve remotely. So the agenda for this particular module is we're going to start off by talking
about the core features available in jQuery when it comes to AJAX, and specifically we'll focus on some of
the functions that are there. From there, we'll talk about how we can get HTML data easily into an application.
And this is really useful actually. You may just want to load help content as a user clicks on something, or
you might want to actually load parts of a page, but instead of just returning say JSON data or XML, you're
actually just going to return HTML that the server renders and then update the DOM with that HTML.
We'll also talk about how we can make GET and then POST requests.
And so GET requests are just, you do this every day when you type the link into the browser and hit Enter.
That would be a GET request, or any time you load a script using the source attribute of the script tag, that's
a GET request to the server. We'll talk about that, and then we'll also talk about post, which allows us to
send more data to the server. So post is similar, but different way it works behind the scenes.
And then we'll introduce finally the AJAX function. Now the ones I just mentioned we're going to talk about
that allow us to load and get and post and those types of things, really they rely on, there's a kind of underlying
function called AJAX that gives you all the power. It's the most low level API for AJAX, it gives you the
most flexibility, but it does require a little bit more coding to use.
I actually prefer AJAX in general and I usually will write wrapper functions around it because it gives me
the ultimate in flexibility. So we'll talk about all those and then you can choose which one you'd like to
use in your application when you want to exchange data back and forth between a browser and the server.