If you need complete control over how an ajax request is made from the client up to the server and how the
response is handled, then you can use jQuery's ajax function. So in this demonstration, I'm going to show
you how to use that function. Now of course if you're doing more simple things like you just need to get some
JSON data, you need to get some HTML, you need to get a post, then I've already covered in the previous portions
of this module some demonstrations and information about the load, the get, the post, getJSON, and those
types of shortcut functions, and really they're just wrappers around the ajax function that I'm going to show
here. But if you want complete control over how the request is made and want to be able to tweak things here
or there, then if you go with the ajax function you can do that because it gives you really fine grain control
over the different parameters. So, to start, you can see that I have, let me switch the design actually,
a textbox for First Name and a textbox for Last Name, then a simple button.
Now what we'd like to do is when the user fills in this information and hits submit, I'd like to make an ajax
request up to the server, using the ajax function of course, and I want to pass this up as a JSON object.
The server is then going to handle that and convert it in this case to a C# object, we'll simulate an insertion
into the database, and then we're going to return a different type of object, which will be serialized to
JSON for processing with jQuery. So that's all shown right here.
You can see I have this operation called InsertCustomer, it accepts a customer object and has a cust parameter.
Now this'll be important, you'll see this in just a second. You'll notice it returns an OperationStatus object.
Now the OperationStatus object just holds some state about what's going on.
So if you're in debug mode you could pass the StackTrace, otherwise you can pass things like the InsertedID,
the Message, true or false, did it work. The customer object, very simple, it just has the customer ID, the
FirstName, and the LastName. Okay, so that's kind of what's going to happen from the server side.
Now, this could be Ruby on Rails, it could be PHP, some type of Python framework, it really doesn't matter.
I'm using WCF in this example just to demonstrate the concept, but keep in mind, you can do this with anything
that can handle the different formats, JSON, XML, even text. Alright, so once the customer is passed up,
we'll kind of simulate and insert and we're going to return an OperationStatus object.
We're going to simulate that it worked, have an ID, and then have a message about what was just done.
So let's switch back over to here and you'll notice that the button is already wired up to the shortcut click
function in jQuery. So what I'd like to do first is I need to go grab the values of the textboxes and convert
those, I'm going to convert them into a JSON object. So we're going to call that customer.
Now remember that we need to pass up this parameter called cust.
And the way we're going to do that is we're actually going to say cust equals, that'll be the name, and then
the value is actually going to be a JSON object, but I need to convert that JSON object into a string.
So first let me just create the JSON object and then I'll show you a technique for converting it.
So we're going to grab the FirstName from this particular guy right there, the textbox, and then we're going
to grab the LastName and we'll grab it from this textbox. Okay, so that's our simple JSON object that we're
ultimately going to pass up to the server. Now the problem is I need to get this in a string format because
I need the name and the value, name as a string, value as a string.
This is going to make a GET request, so it's going to put it on the querystring.
So the way I can convert what really is a JavaScript object into a string is we can use a JSON stringify script.
Now the JSON stringify script is available if you go to JSON.org, and Douglas Crockford wrote it who has a lot
to do, pretty much all the main stuff with JSON, and we're going to use that script, which I've already referenced
so you can see right here, to actually stringify this, or convert it to a string.
So the way you do that is once you have the script reference, you can say JSON.stringify, and then in parentheses
you can give it the value that you want to stringify there. So what that'll do is basically convert this
JavaScript object that's up in memory at this point once it runs into a string, we'll then assign that, and
kind of concatenate it together with our name. So we have our name and our value, we're ready to go.
Okay, so that's what I'm going to send up to the server. Now, to send it up to the server we're going to use
the ajax function. And so I'm going to actually pass into it the JSON object parameter.
And so this allows us complete control over the different things we want to do.
So we're going to go in and I'm going to say the url property is going to be, and I'm currently in the UsingAjax
folder, but I want to call into this service. So we're going to say dot dot to go up one, or you could certainly
go from the root of your site, and we'll say CustomerService.svc/InsertCustomer, and that's that operation
that you just saw on the server side. The data we want to pass is our customer.
Now the dataType that we're going to get back is going to be json data, that's what we want back.
The final two things I'm going to add, I'm going to add a success function, and for that we're going to have
the data, the string status code, and then the XMLHttpRequest object, should we need it.
And then finally, I'm going to add an error property, and we'll add a function for that that looks like this,
XMLHttpRequest, the status, and any error information. Okay, now in the error function I'm just going to
come into here and we'll just say alert Error occurred, nothing real fancy on this one, and we'll pass it the
status. So I'm not going to do much there, but what I'd like to do with the success is I want to update this
div that's right below the button. So I'm going to grab that, we'll do an ID selector, get my pound on the front.
Okay, now I'm going to update the HTML of it and we're going to kind of keep it simple to start.
We're just going to say Insert status, and we want to know did it work or not.
So I can pass in the data, and this is going to be the JSON data that's passed back.
Now just as a real quick review, remember I'm passing back this OperationStatus object, so we should have
access to these properties using JSON. So right now I just want to write out true to get it going.
So we're going to say data, and because this is a default configure WCF Service, it'll wrap the JSON in a d
property value, .Status. And we'll update the HTML of our div down here with that particular value.
Alright, so let's go ahead and we'll call into that. We'll hit Submit and you can see that's working great.
So let's also write out, we can of course get to the Message. And so let's go ahead and do that.
So I'm going to wrap this down so we can see it a little bit better, and we'll say we want the Status plus, let's
go ahead and do a line break, and then we'll do data.d.Message.
So this will grab us the actual value that we're going to get back in the OperationStatus message and there
we go, Customer Inserted, John Doe. If we go back over into the service, you'll see that's indeed what was
passed back, Customer Inserted, and then it's going to be John Doe because that's what we passed up.
So, this shows how you can use the ajax function to control really whatever you want to control, and there's
a lot of additional properties that you can configure. This is a GET request.
For instance, we might want to turn the caching on or off based on what we're doing.
Now gets are going to be cached by default, but we may not want to do that.
So there's a lot we can do there. Now if you go over to the jQuery documentation and click on Ajax on the left
there and go into this ajax function, I showed a little bit of this earlier, but I use this overload, so I
actually pass the URL by using the URL property, but we could have done it up here as well, you can see in jQuery
1.5, which I'm running right now, but if we come on down, for instance I could come in and say hey, I want to
set the cache to true or false based on what we're doing. And so if set to false, it's going to force requested
pages not to be cached by the browser, and that may or may not be good depending on what you're doing.
So a lot of different things. The contentType of the data being sent up we can also control through the contentType
property and there's a lot of stuff. jQuery 1.5 adds some converter and filter features that are nice, you
can see that here, and the list goes on, so, we used a few of these though.
Now, something I've used it for, and I'm not going to demo it here, but I at least want to bring it up is JSONP
requests, cross-domain requests where you're not calling back to a page or service on your server domain,
you're calling another one that you trust. Well, you can do that with the AJAX function as well.
So, it's very, very flexible and there's some information about that on the jQuery documentation page.
So that's an example of doing it. Just to show you what's going on behind the scenes, I have Fiddler fired
up here, let me go ahead and remove all session. And I've shown this in a couple other demos.
Let's go ahead and run it and let's see what's going on behind the scenes with our data.
So, because it's localhost, I'm going to put a dot right there so Fiddler will recognize this, we'll submit
it, hit Submit, get back our data. Let's go check out Fiddler now and it should be this bottom one, and yeah,
there we go. So here's our get. You'll notice that the cust equals, and there's our kind of stringified version
of our call that was made. And we can see the types being sent up, the XMLHttpRequest was used, and here's
what was sent back. So again, because it was a WCF kind of default configured service, it wraps it in the d,
the type of the object passed back is OperationStatus, and then we have all that other data that we just wrote out.
So really, really nice for inspecting your data. So that's an example of using AJAX.
It definitely is a little more involved, but at the same time if you need that control, it's really, really
nice to work with and I think because it allows you to pass in a JSON object, I think it's pretty easy to work with.
They have really good documentation on the page, on the jQuery.com site.
So, that's how you can get started with it, you've now seen the whole gamut of them, we've seen get, we've
seen post, getJSON, load, and then here's the most low level API that's available in jQuery for AJAX calls.