In this module, we've talked about a lot of the different features available in jQuery that make it easy to
work with AJAX. Specifically, we focused on a few key of the key functions available such as load, get,
getJSON, post, and AJAX, and I've showed you how those can be integrated into your jQuery applications.
Load, as we talked about, allows you to load HTML content from a server, and very easily assign that HTML
into a given selected DOM node. So you simply give it a selector, call .load, and then give it the URI, URL,
whatever you want to call it, and it'll go out and grab that. We also talked about the get.
Now get provides a little more flexibility because it doesn't do just HTML, it can also do JSON and HTML and
XML. And then we talked about getJSON, which of course is a GET request, but specific to retrieving JavaScript
object notation data. We also talked about a little bit of a difference between get and post, and I showed
how post really is the same API as get, it's just that it executes a post request to the server.
And then finally, I showed how ajax is the core, the low level API function that's available in jQuery that
really all of the others tie into and use. So the sky is the limit when it comes to working with AJAX and jQuery
because you can work with all kinds of different data, the cross-browser issues aren't issues because that's
abstracted out from us, and it's just really easy to get going and actually I think kind of a pleasure to
work with, it makes it fun to exchange data and to add those cool features into your web applications.