JQuery provides excellent support for performing asynchronous JavaScript and XML calls to a server, AJAX.
Now the term AJAX is a little bit misleading now days because most developers aren't actually sending and
receiving XML data from the server. Now you can do that, and some are certainly, but normally if you're
using AJAX now days, you're probably using JSON data, JavaScript object notation, or maybe even sending just
raw HTML data back and forth. Regardless, jQuery supports all of those.
It does support XML data as far as getting the data or sending the data, JSON data and HTML, and it makes it
very easy to work with. Now AJAX in a nutshell is simply a way to update parts of a page without reloading
the whole page. So in a lot of apps out there, that are web-based anyway, you'll typically have to wait when
you click a button or a drop-down or whatever it is for the entire page to reload.
AJAX calls allow us to kind of take out entire page reloads out of the equation, and instead when the user
clicks a button, we might just reload parts of the page. It makes our apps way more efficient as far as the
end user goes, whether or not the performance is better, it definitely seems, the perceived performance is
better, and normally in most cases it will be better because you're not reloading all of the data for an entire
page. So throughout the module we'll be talking about some functions, which I'll show you in just a moment,
that'll allow us to make AJAX calls. And the nice part about this is we can do it in a cross-browser way.
Now IE6 definitely does it differently than all the other browsers, and we know that IE6 is still hanging
around out there unfortunately. And as a result, we still have to deal with it.
So the nice thing about jQuery, it abstracts all that out, we don't have to worry about what the browsers
support, it tests that for us and then applies it appropriately so that we can either load an ActiveX control,
if it's say IE6, or if it's IE7, IE8, IE9, Chrome, Safari, Firefox, and the others, then there's a built-in
object that's available to use. Now to see why that's important and the differences, let me pull up a little
page here that illustrates this.
So here's an example from Microsoft on how things have changed between IE6 and IE7, and then on up of course.
Most of the major browsers now days have a built-in XMLHttpRequest object, and so it's just a native object
that you can call using the new keyword. Well, prior to IE7, you had to actually use an ActiveXObject.
So you'd create a new ActiveXObject and then give it a different string depending on the version and things
that you wanted to use. So jQuery automatically takes care of that type of code for us, and a lot of other
issues that are associated with that, so that we don't have to worry about it, and that's nice.
And what's really nice about it is that we can do this with just a few simple functions that we can call into.
So let's take a look at those.
So here's some of the functions that jQuery provides. We have the load.
Loads typically use when you want to load HTML data. This could be useful, for instance, in a help scenario
where maybe there's a little question mark icon, and when the user clicks it, you want to go out to the server,
and based on what they clicked, grab the HTML content for that particular topic and then show it.
Well, you don't want to reload the whole page just to load some help, so this makes it very easy to do it.
We're still going to make a request to the server, but we're going to do it in a way that's very fast and performant.
We also have get and post functions, and these allow us to do what they match up with.
We could do a GET request or a POST request and work with it. If you want to get JSON data, there's actually
a getJSON API function, and this is one I use a fair amount because I'm typically working with JSON data when
I'm sending data back and forth from the server. Now when it comes to sending HTML, XML or JSON, JSON is definitely
when it goes over the wire, pretty dang efficient. So something that's good to do.
Now it does mean when you get the data back in your script, you're going to have to write code to pull the data
out of the JSON, which is very simple, I'll show you that coming up in the demos, but you'll have to do that,
pull it out, and then update the DOM. Now the final function is the kind of low level API, which is AJAX.
Now I use this one probably the most out of any of the others, and the reason for that is it gives you the full
power available to use. So AJAX allows you to specify things like content types and what's the URL to call,
what type of data am I getting back. You can specify different callbacks for errors and success and stuff
like that. So when we walk through these, I'll show the differences and explain how they work.
Now all of these can be used to call REST APIs, you could even call web services if they return the appropriate
data for your application, or just native HTML URLs, if that's what you want to call as well.
So let's delve into the different functions here and I'll show you some demos and examples of how these
different functions can work. We're going to start off with the load function.
So let me talk about what it does and then I'll show you how it works.