JQuery provides a really simple way to load HTML content from a remote server, and you can do this through
the load function. So in this section, we're going to talk about the load function and the different parameter
values that can be passed in. So here's an example of the signature of the load function.
You can see that we can pass in a URL, we can pass in some data, which you'll see in a moment could be something
like JSON data that gets passed up to the server, and then you can have a callback function, which we'll see
at the end of this section. Now the only one of these three that you have to pass is the URL.
So let's look at an example of that first. So moving on down, you'll notice we're going to handle the DOM
ready, and then we're going to wire up a button and the click event specifically to this callback function.
Now when that button is clicked, we're going to go ahead and go out to HelpDetails.html, you'll notice this
is a relative URL, so it's going to load it relative to the current page where this is running, and when that
data comes back, we're going to place it inside of this MyDiv ID selector.
So with one simple line of code, jQuery can go out to the server, grab the HTML data, and then automatically
append it to my div here. It makes it really nice and easy to work with.
Now there may be cases though when you want to do a load, but you don't want to put the entire content of this
HelpDetails.html. A real life example would be if you had some type of help documentation in HelpDetails,
then you might want to filter that based on what they clicked on to give context-sensitive details.
So an example of that is shown here. And you'll notice that we do the standard load.
So we have the ID selector that determines what the data, where the data I should say, goes into, my div, we
call .load, we give it HelpDetails.html, but you'll notice that we do an ID selector on MainTOC.
Now this is the context of the selector, it's not the document we're currently working with, it's the document
we just loaded, that's why it's in the string here. So what's going to happen is it's going to go out, load
HelpDetails.html, then filter that data by this ID selector, place the return result, all the nodes that are
returned into the children of my div. So it makes it really easy to filter.
Now, it's not going to do this at the server, it is going to download this HTML document, then it will filter
based on my TOC and apply it to MyDiv. So unfortunately it's not going to be a really efficient thing if you
had a huge, huge page because it is going to download the entire page and then it will do the filter in there,
but it is fairly useful if HelpDetails just needs to be downloaded once and cached, then you could apply
different ID selectors to it and it makes it pretty interesting.
So really, really easy to work with you can see. Now the second parameter you can pass is the data.
So data can be passed to the server in cases where it needs to return something based upon that data.
So in this example, we're going to call Customers.aspx, and by doing that, we don't want to return all the
customers. This example, which I'll run in the demo coming up will simply return columnar data.
So customer data in columns, but we only want to return 25 customers in this example to be placed inside of MyDiv.
So what this'll do, is you can see the second parameter, you pass in a JSON object, we have a PageSize property
with a value of 25, that'll be passed up to GetCustomers.aspx. In this case, C# code will then analyze the
page size and determine how many customers to return back. Now keep in mind this could be PHP, this could be
Python, Java, it doesn't really matter. It works with anything as long as it can return HTML data to you.
So really useful though if you need to pass some data up to the server and the server expects that data, and
you can of course pass more than one property, since we're only showing one in this example.
So that's the second parameter, the data. Now you can also go in and have a third parameter, which is optional
as well, which is a callback function. Now this one uses two of the three parameters.
So you can see in the code here we have this NotFound.html that we're going to tie into.
Now, that purposely is named that way because it doesn't exist on the server we're going to assume, so we
just want to demonstrate in this example how we can have a callback function that can check the status of the
message, and if it's an error, then we can grab some details about that error.
So the three parameters passed into the callback function shown here are the response, the data coming back,
status, which is going to be if we're an error or not, and then the XMLHttpRequest object will have details
about the error if there is one that occurred. Now in this case, since NotFound isn't available, then this
will definitely give an error, the function will be called either way, success or failure, we'll detect that
we had an error, and then we'll ride out the status message to an alert.
So really nice in situations where you need to determine if it worked or not, and then write your code to
handle the situation where maybe it didn't. And so let's take a look at a demonstration of how we can use
the load function with some of these different parameter options.