Let's take a look at how we can load HTML content from a remote server into our web application with just a
little bit of code using our load function. So you can see I have a reference to jQuery, and at the time of
this last module, jQuery 1.5 had just come out, so we're going to show that, and we're going to use our standard
ready. So we'll say document.ready, we'll give it our function, and there we go.
So now what I'm going to do is when this button is clicked with an ID of MyButton, I'd like to go in and grab
some HTML that's going to be located in this HelpDetails.html file.
So the first thing I'm going to do is add a selector for MyButton, so let's go ahead and do that, and then we'll
add a click, and when it's clicked we're going to execute a function here as well.
Now I want to do the load. So I'm just putting a comment and say Load HTML from HelpDetails.html.
So let me open this file and you'll see that this one actually has the body and the head and the HTML tag striped
out, we just have the core HTML that we need mainly because if this is only going to be used for loading parts
of a page, then there's really no reason to load all the other stuff because it obviously adds to the HTML
payload, so we want to keep that minimal. Now this one is pretty simple.
You could see that we have a div with a MainTOC that goes to there, and that just links down to some anchors here.
Alright, so it'll load that, we can just use our simple load function, it's about as easy as it can get, and
I want to load it down into here. So we can come in, we'll do an ID selector on that, and we'll simply say load.
And you'll notice that I'm only getting a, b, c as the parameters.
Now we happen to know what those mean at this point, we have the URI, we have the data for the b, and we have
a function callback. Now the reason I'm not getting the full IntelliSense is for this particular project I
don't have the vsdoc file, so you can see how it really adds a lot if you looked at the demos in the previous
modules because in those I have the vsdoc file in place, so definitely you probably want that.
Now, what we're going to do is pass in the URL, so I need to go up a level.
I'm going to do this relative to this current page, and so we have UsingLoad, and if we go up from there we
can get to this particular guy. So we could go from either the root of the server or we can just go up, I'm going
to keep it simple, and so we'll say HelpDetails.html. And that's it, so we're only going to pass one of the
possible three parameters that you can pass in the load. Now if we go ahead and run this, we'll click the
button and you can see how fast it loads that. Now it's local, so of course it's going to be really fast, but
it's still very good performance and it automatically updated the OutputDiv for us and didn't have to write
a lot of code to do it, very, very nice. Now the other thing that you can do with this, as I showed earlier,
is we can come in and let me open HelpDetails, and let's say that we only want to load this particular div,
or maybe we have another div in here. In fact, let's just do that, let's just add another one and we'll add
an ID of, we'll call this SubTOC, and I'll just put This is my sub table of contents.
So if we only wanted to load that and display it, we can use an ID selector of SubTOC along with a URI, which
is really kind of clever actually. Now keep in mind it is going to download the entire file, so that part
doesn't change, there's no way to influence that without doing some server side magic there, but at least
when it downloads it, especially if it's cached, then we're going to be able to grab just this piece.
So let's go ahead and do that, and all we have to do is inside of the string for the URI, we can simply put our
ID selector of SubTOC, very, very simple. So now we'll go ahead and View in Browser, and there we go.
This is my sub table of contents. So what's nice about this is at this point it's cached, and the reason for
that is this by default, as I mentioned earlier, is a GET request.
Now if I do pass in data as the second parameter, we pass in some type of JSON object, then it's going to switch
over to a post, and then it won't be cached, but at this stage it is cached, so now it's going to be really,
really performant, really fast to work with. So that's a super easy thing we can do there.
Now we can also come in, and as I showed earlier we can load with a callback.
So I already have all the code done here, so we're going to hook up our HelpButton to a function when it's
clicked, but when we load, NotFound.html is nowhere to be found actually, that's why it's called NotFound,
and as a result, we want to be able to handle that error. So this'll call the function that you see right here.
So what'll happen because it's not found, we'll get a particular error.
So let me go ahead and run it. Hit Get HTML and you can see Error is error.
Now just to show that that actually got called, there's Error plus the statusText of our XMLHttpRequest object.
And there's even more details we can get through that object as well, but this provides an easy way to see,
do we have an error or not, and then we can act upon that, so pretty simple to use.
The other thing we can do is pass data up. Now this example calls a dynamic page, it could be PHP, it could
be Python, it could be Pearl, it could be whatever it is you're using on the server side, but the server side
in this case is an ASP.NET page and it accepts a page size of 10.
So this is our own custom JavaScript object notation object and you'll see GetCustomers right here, so let me
show you that. This uses a DataList control that's part of ASP.NET to simply write out dynamically some trs
and tds columnar data based upon customers. You can see we have a HeaderTemplate, an ItemTemplate representing
each row, and then we have our FooterTemplate here. Well that part is specific to ASP.NET, so that may change
obviously if you're doing PHP or something else, but we can come into the code behind here, the actual code
that drives it, and what I want to point out is when the request comes in to this page, we're going to grab
the PageSize. Now if there isn't one passed we're going to default to 50.
Otherwise, we're going to take that PageSize that was passed in, convert it to an integer, and then we're
going to use that to just really render some fake customers here.
We'll have John 1, John 2, and so forth. We'll then take those customers, we'll bind it into our DataList,
and then output the HTML through these calls right here. So if we run this, it's nice because we're able to
hit a dynamic page even though this is just the simple load function and we're able to pass up our PageSize.
So let me go ahead and run that. And now that it's loaded let's go ahead and click Get HTML and there we go.
So you can see we passed up the page size and it returned the specific number of objects here based upon, let
me go back to that, based upon the loop that we were doing. So we're actually doing while it's less than the
PageSize. So, very easy to change that. We can come in, let's go ahead and up that to say 25.
And if we run it now, you'll see that we get the appropriate number of customers while it's less than 25.
So, very, very nice, very easy. So load is not just for hardcoded HTML pages, you can also use it for dynamic
situations, and that's why the particular data parameter here that the load accepts is really useful because
now we can pass in some different data based upon what the end user wants to see.
So that's an example of using the load function. Very, very easy way to get HTML into your applications.