The load function provides a great way to load HTML content from the server, but there's going to be times
when you want to be more flexible. You might want JSON data, XML data, HTML or just even simple strings of text.
So in this section we're going to talk about another function that's available in jQuery called get, and get
gives you more flexibility for making these GET requests as the name implies.
So you'll notice in the signature of the get that we have $.get, so you don't give it a selector first, you
say really it's like doing jQuery.get, the jQuery object has this get function hanging off of it.
So we call it a global function. And the first three parameters are the same, the URL, any data that gets
passed up, a callback function, but we also have the option if we need to pass in the dataType, and this
can be XML, HTML, JSON or even raw strings, and you can even do scripts this way if needed.
So in this example, we're going to use the get function directly.
So again, notice it's a little bit different than some of the, most of the stuff actually we've covered in
the course because usually we do it through a selector. Well in this case, because get is a global function
off of the jQuery object, we can just call it directly, we're going to say go grab this HTML, but instead of
the load automatically updating the HTML, we have to write some code to do that because after all, we didn't
give it a selector on where that HTML should go. So you could see that we have a callback function, which
passes in the HTML data, if that's the case, which it would be with this one, and then we're going to go do
an ID selector and update ultimately the innerHTML with the html data that was returned.
So with get, you have to write a little bit more code, however, you could still do a GET request just like a
load does by default, but you have more control over not only the dataType, but also how the data that comes
back gets updated. It provides a very useful feature that's simple to use though.
It's interesting to note while we're on this, obviously a get does a GET request, but a load by default does
a get, however, if you pass in data as the second parameter, it'll actually fall back to a POST request in
that scenario. So one of the useful tools I like to use is the jQuery source code viewer that I want to show
you real quick because sometimes you might want to know what are these jQuery functions doing behind the scenes.
For instance, how did I know that load is hardcoded to always use HTML data and how's that look versus get?
So let me show you an example of that.
Now you should always go to the HTML documentation through jQuery at the api.jquery.com because that'll
provide some great details on the parameters and things that are passed.
And so if you go there and you want to use the AJAX functionality, if we go back to All, we'll see what you would
see by default, we'll hit on Ajax, and that gives us all the AJAX features.
And here's get, here's the four parameters we were just talking through.
Now the jQuery source viewer that I find useful is something I use in times where I read the docs, but I'm a
little bit unsure about how one particular parameter is used. Well, if you go to this URL here, and I'll
probably say the last name wrong, but james., I'm assuming it's padolsey.com/jquery, then you can get to this
jQuery source viewer. And this actually allows you to type in functions, even select versions, and then it
will go in and provide the source code of what is jQuery actually doing behind the scenes.
Now this is also a great way to learn scripting techniques, but we won't bother with that now.
What I want to show you though is that behind the scenes, it looks like the get is actually making an AJAX request.
Now you'll also notice it hardcodes the type of the request to be a GET request, but the dataType of the response
that's going to come back is not hardcoded. That comes up from that fourth parameter if it's supplied.
If it's not, it'll figure it out, or try to, on the fly. And then you'll notice we can pass in the URL, any
data, and then here's our callback. Now we're going to be talking about the AJAX function later in this
module, so I'm not going to go into details here, but you'll see that all the AJAX functions available in
jQuery are going to be relying on that. Now if we go to the load function, which we've already looked at,
you'll see with the load function that here's those three parameters, and if I scroll on down a little bit,
it also uses the AJAX function behind the scenes, but the dataType is hardcoded to be HTML.
So whereas the get function we're talking about now allows flexibility there, you can pass HTML, XML, JSON,
even a script or a string as the dataType, the get is way more flexible whereas the load, it hardcodes it to
be HTML. So I like to use this particular source code viewer to kind of see what's going on behind the scenes,
learn a bit about what jQuery is doing, and it's a great learning tool as well for learning some nice JavaScript
techniques.
Now in addition to the get function, we also have a global one called getJSON.
Now getJSON pretty much does what is says, it uses the get to grab some JSON data from the server.
Now you'll notice the parameters are identical to the load. So we have the URL, the data to pass up to the
server, if any, and then a callback. Now those are illustrated here.
So we call through the jQuery object, we call getJSON, and now we need to pass it the API, the docs, whether
it's Pearl or Python or ASP.NET, the document or web service or REST API, whatever you want to call it, that
is capable of returning this data to us. So in this case, CustomerJson.aspx is going to return JSON data of
course, we're going to pass up to the page an ID property of 1, so it'll grab 1 customer.
Once that data is returned back, that'll be passed into our callback function as this data parameter, and
because it is JSON data, we can just get to the properties of the JSON data directly.
So, we have a FirstName property and a LastName property it looks like in this scenario, which will simply
pop up into an alert. So it's a very, very easy way to work with JSON data.
Now you could certainly do the same thing with the get going back to here.
Instead of passing HTML, I can definitely pass a page name or a service, a REST API that allows me to get back
JSON and process it, but if you're always just going to be working with JSON directly, this definitely is a
little bit easier to work with in that particular case. So let's look at an example of using the get and the
getJSON functions with jQuery in some code here.