The get function provides a simple way to perform a get against a server that provides up some data, and so
I'm going to show you an example of how we can interact with that and use it in an application.
So you can see that we have a button here, and this will be a pretty common theme throughout the AJAX demos,
you've seen this in the load, we'll see it in the post, and even in the AJAX.
But when that MyButton is clicked, we want to execute the function here, and so what I'd like to do is call
the global function called get, and we're going to call into this HelpDetails now.
If you saw the load tutorial, the demonstration then you've already seen this, it just contains some simple
data in it that we want to display. So if we want to go ahead and do a GET request instead of using the load,
then we could simply put in the URL, so I'm going to go up one level with the dot dot there, and then we're going
to give it a callback. And inside of here, when the data comes, unlike load, which automatically loads it
into the selector we would have supplied, we have to tell it. So we have the OutputDiv here and we're simply
going to select that with an ID selector. And we'll update the HTML with the data, so very, very simple.
Now, not as simple as load, but we do have a little more flexibility because when we get back this data, we
could certainly do something with it instead of just updating it, but let's go ahead and run it.
And when we click the button here, we should see the HTML content come back and we're pretty much in business,
we're ready to go. We can also go in and we can use the get to get other types of data.
So you'll notice over here I have a Customerjson.aspx. And as mentioned throughout these, it could certainly
be PHP or some other format if you'd like, but what we're going to do is simply set the content type being
returned to JSON, we're going to take a customer, and we're going to serialize it to JSON data and simply
write it out to the Response.OutputStream. So we're going to take this customer, take an ID that's passed
in, add it to the ID right here, and then return it. So this is C#, but in essence we're just taking an object
in memory and serializing it down to JSON. So if we wanted to call this using the get, then we can do really
the same type of approach. So I'm going to copy this, except we're going to use all the different parameters
here. When I type in the get, you'll notice it takes four parameters, as was talked about.
So we can pass in the URI, we can pass in data, we can pass in a callback function, and we can even specify the
type of data we want to deal with. So we have the URI, but I'm going to go ahead and change that now, and let's
change that to CustomerJson. I'm going to pass in data for the ID and just to kind of confirm, I'm actually
going to match the case there just to keep it consistent, and we'll do an id of say 5, there's our callback,
we'll go ahead and do something with that. And then finally after the callback, we're going to say we're
going to work with JSON data. So now we can come in and once we get this data back, we can obviously do something
with it in our callback. So for this example, let me just go ahead and just do an alert to start off and let's
do data., and we should be able to get to the FirstName property that was specified right here, which should
be John. So very much like what we saw up above, the difference being that number one, we're going to supply
some data, number two we're going to specify the type of data we want to work with.
And actually it looks like we need to fix that. So let me go ahead and run this and you can see we get back John.
So as expected, we get the data and we're pretty much good to go.
Let's just go ahead and fill this out all the way and we'll do data.LastName.
And let's also put ID, we'll do data.ID, and let me just wrap that down a little bit.
So let's run it now and now we should be able to see that the ID should be 5, so it will basically roundtrip
the ID from the client up to the server and then back. And there we go, we have ID 5 and we have John Doe.
Now, that certainly works, but after all we did talk about a getJSON function, so let's go ahead and take a
look at how we could simplify this and not have to specify for instance this parameter if we just want to get
JSON anyway, it's a lot easier to work with if we just use that function directly.
So let me go over to this particular area and we're going to do the same type of thing, when the button here
is clicked, we want to go in and do something with it. So we'll just pop up an alert again in this example,
but we're not going to do get, we're going to do getJSON. And so I'm going to call that same exact CustomerJson.aspx
that I saw earlier, we'll pass in an id, we'll do 5 again, and then from there we need our callback function.
So we're going to get our JSON data back and we're going to go ahead and end that right here.
So inside of the data, now it's the same thing as you just saw, so we can come in and we can do an alert.
In fact, let me just go ahead and grab what we've already done since we already know that's the type of data,
and we'll pass that in. So it's pretty similar overall of course, but we don't have to specify the parameter
here. In fact, let's take a look at the signature and you see we only have three, we have the URI we want to
call, or URL, we have the data, that's the b, and then the c would be our callback function.
So let's go ahead and run that, and same thing. So, a little bit simpler, but really the same effect as calling
get. I'm a pretty big fan of hey, if you don't have to type extra code, let's not type extra code, and you can
see that keeps it pretty easy to work with. So that's an example of using get and getJSON to be able to call
and get different types of data in our applications.