GET requests are really useful in jQuery and through the get, the load, or the getJSON you can make those,
but anytime you make a GET request, it's going to be cached in the browser by default if that's how it's setup,
and you are limited on the amount of data that can be passed up because the data is going to actually be encoded
and placed on the URL. Well, sometimes you might want to make a request that there's a lot more data involved,
large amounts of data are posted up, in that case you probably are going to want to go with a POST request.
Now POST requests are not cached in the browser, so when you make a POST request in jQuery, there won't be
any caching going on due to the nature of a post, but you do have that advantage of being able to post large
amounts of data, just like you do with a form, you might fill out a large form, and that's going to be a post.
So the post function, the API looks identical to what you're used to with the get and the getJSON that we just
saw. You're going to have a URL, the data, and the callback. Now all three of those are used with load, get,
and getJSON, and then of course the get also had a datatype you can pass in, which we've talked about can be
XML, JSON, HTML, and even some others. So the call itself looks identical to the get.
In fact, you'll see it's a global function right off of the jQuery object, but in this case we're going to
actually post PageSize of 15, this JSON object, up to GetCustomers.aspx.
In this case it looks like it's going to return html data based on what the code is doing, and we also didn't
pass in a datatype here, so jQuery tries to figure that out for you.
So the data will come in, we'll go ahead and update the innerHTML of this particular div.
So that's pretty standard in what we've seen to this point and really just almost identical to what we did
with the get. Now let's look at some other examples of post here and what you can do with it.
Post can also be used to hook up to, if you're doing .NET, services such as WCF Services.
And I want to point out something that's a little bit unique with this.
So in this example, you'll see we're going to post data up to a Windows Communication Foundation Service,
or WCF Service. We can tell because of the .svc extension. Now if you're not doing .NET, you can probably
skip forward here and jump right to the demo, but for those of you that are, when you call a WCF Service, you
can mark the service using some different attributes as JSON-enabled operations.
So this GetCustomers is what we call an operation, and what it's going to do is by default return SOAP, Simple
Object Access Protocol, but you can also configure it with WebGet and WebInvoke attributes to return JSON data.
Now, by default though, when WCF, if you just hook it up the normal way, returns JSON data, when this callback
gets passed in, you'll notice that we say data., but we're going to go to this d object.
Well, what'll happen is the JSON data that's returned will be wrapped with this d object, so d will actually
be the name of it representing I suppose data, and we're going to say let's go into the data by going to the 0.
So in this case, once we get that, we're going to store that as our cust object representing our customer,
and then we can get into the FirstName and LastName, and that's something that you definitely might have to
play with if you've ever called into a WCF Service and can't figure out why you can't get the data properly.
Now what I like to do to figure that type of stuff out when I'm having problems is use a tool called Fiddler,
and let me pull that up real quick and show you how you can get this free tool.
If you pull up your browser and go to fiddle2.com, you can get to the Fiddler site.
The tool itself is actually a desktop app. It's one that I use a lot.
In fact, you can see right down here on my toolbar I have Fiddler, and what Fiddler is an HTTP proxy tool.
It allows you to inspect traffic as you're making AJAX calls, or really any HTTP calls, and it will show you
what's going on with the messaging. It's really easy to use. So, of I pull it up, in the user interface you'll
see a request will be made right off the bat out to the Fiddler site to check the versions.
You can see this updatecheck.asp isBeta False, and so over on the left side here, this is where all your
requests would be made. So if we make an AJAX request, then it'll show up in here, and then if we go over to
TextView, we can actually see it doesn't look like any data was sent up other than the isBeta False on the
querystring, but if we come down into TextView here, we can see that some information was returned back,
which looks like it's the version data for the most current version of Fiddler.
So you can actually use this to inspect your messages, and in the demo coming up, I'm going to actually show
you how to use that with your POST requests. It makes it really easy to inspect your data.
So POST requests are really useful any time you want to pass up some data to a service, which you can get away
with a get, but sometimes you might have nested objects and it's difficult to mark that up in a way that
it fits on the URL, or you might have large enough amounts of data that you just can't trust the fact it's
going to fit on the URL, some of them might be truncated or chopped off.
So, now that we've talked about load, get, and post, and specifically focused on post here, let's look at an
example of how it can be used within a web application.