So up to this point in the module, you've seen demos on how to use the load function to use HTML and how to use
the get function when you want to make a GET request to the server.
But there may be times when you want to execute a POST request. Now post, as I mentioned earlier, doesn't
allow the actual URL and the contents to be cached by default, and that's just how a post works.
The benefit though is you can post large amounts of data whereas when you do a get, you're limited to what
can be passed on the querystring, and there is a limit to that.
So to demonstrate the post, we're going to do really the equivalent of the get, very, very similar to what I
did earlier. But let's go ahead and we're going to call into GetCustomers.aspx, and just as a refresher,
when this particular page on the server runs, it's going to check up on the querystring, or in this case in
the request collection because we're doing a post, and it's going to say hey, do we have a PageSize.
So it'll either check the querystring or the form collection. In this case, because it's a post it'll be in
the form collection. And if there isn't one, we'll return 50, otherwise we'll convert that to an integer
and we're going to use that to just simply create some customers on the fly here.
So it'll return an HTML table. So let me go up to GetCustomers.aspx, we're going to pass up that PageSize I
just showed you, we'll just do 15 in this case, and then we have our callback function.
Now this is going to pass us the data. So, we'll come into here and now what we want to do is simply grab our
OutputDiv, do an ID selector on that, very simple, and we're going to update the HTML with the data because
that's what this page returns is some HTML data. So if we go ahead and run that, let's do View in Browser,
and you can see it works. Now I mentioned in the section about posts that there's some nice tools available
out there that you can actually inspect the traffic going back and forth, and one of those tools is Fiddler.
So, what I'm going to do is open up Fiddler, and as I mentioned this is an HTTP proxy tool, so it allows you
to actually view the traffic going back and forth between the client and the server, the browser and the server.
So I'm going to go ahead and let's remove the call that Fiddler first makes to check the version to make sure
it's the latest, and we're going to go ahead and just minimize it, but keep it going, and let me reload the
page and hit the button and let's see what we get here. We get nothing, not good.
Okay, well that's actually by design in this case. What's going on is the way localhost works, Fiddler can't
tie into that, it's an internal IP to the operating system, so it doesn't actually see that traffic.
So there's a couple options here. One is I could use my machine name if I had it setup to support that.
In this case though, I'm going to use the second trick, and the second trick is you simply put a dot to basically
trick it so that it still works on localhost, but it doesn't really think it's localhost, it's I don't know,
a quasi localhost I guess, and I'm going to hit Enter. Now this will load up and let's go check Fiddler at
this point and there we go. So there's the request being made, there's also a request out to look at the favicon,
we don't have one, here's a request to get jQuery, and you can see what it's requesting right up here in the
Request Headers. So you can see we have a GET request, another GET request, and then it does a get on the favicon,
which doesn't exist. So let me remove all those now. So we'll come back and now let's hit Get Customers.
It'll go out to the server, return them, and let's go back to Fiddler now.
Okay, so there's our call. First off, it's a POST request, and of course that makes sense, we're using the
post function. And if we look down we can see some information, it looks like this was a form-urlencoded
content type, it was made using the XMLHttpRequest object, here was the Referer, which is the page we're
currently working with. So, if I switch to TextView, we can actually see the data passed from the client up
to the server. And there we go, PageSize of 15, very simple. So this is the request area, this area down here
is the response area. So I can hit TextView and here is the HTML response we got back, and you can actually
hit View in Notepad if you want to pop that up and see it a little bit easier.
Now that's what Fiddler does out of the box, it just allows for a really easy way to see the traffic between
the client and server. And again, you can go, if you go to Help it'll show it here, but you can go to fiddler2.com,
and it was created by Eric Lawrence who, as far as I know, still works up at Microsoft, but fiddler2.com.
Let's go ahead and clear that out, let's leave it going, and we're going to move on to another example of
using post. So the next thing I'm going to do is I showed how we can call into an ASP.NET page, or it could
be a PHP page, it doesn't really matter, but we returned HTML data.
Now let's go into UsingPostToCallAService. Now this is going to be a WCF Service, Windows Communication
Foundation. Now keep in mind it could just as easily be a Java service, it could be based upon Python, there's
many different services of course supported out there. So I'm going to open this up, we're going to right-
click on our .svc file, which represents our service, and go to View Code.
And you can see that there's two operations supported. We have a GetCustomers and then we have this insert
customer. Now we're going to demo the GetCustomers in this particular example.
So it just hardcodes a list of two customers, so we have John Doe and Jane Doe, that are going to be returned,
and we're simply going to write out the first customers, which will be John of First and LastName.
So, although you can certainly just call into more of a REST API, or just a page that returns some data, you
can also call into services that support this type of transaction between the client and the service, or
operation I should say. So let's go ahead and go back into here and what I'd like to do is when we go in and the
button is clicked, so let's go ahead and add that back in, so we'll do MyButton (Typing), and now we're going
to do our global post, so we'll say post, but this time I want to go to the CustomerService.svc.
I don't just want to go to that file though, because remember we have two operations, so I want to call
GetCustomers. And the way we do that is we simply put a slash and we call GetCustomers here.
Now in this one I'm not going to pass any data up, and the reason for that is you'll notice that GetCustomers
doesn't take any data, so we're going to pass null for that, but I also want to come in and we're going to do
a callback function, which is going to be the data. So let's go into here and what I'm going to do now is
grab the first customer, as mentioned, which should be John Doe, and because this is a WCF Service, it'll
actually wrap it in a JSON object called d. So I'm going to say data.d, 0, and that's going to be my first
customer, or I could have done 1 to get into my second customer.
Now to show this works, we're just going to come in and we'll come into our OutputDiv and we'll simply write
out to the html cust.FirstName plus cust.LastName. Now the reason I can do that is if we look, look at the
properties here that are returned from the service, now this is C#, but they'll be serialized for us.
And what'll happen is we'll get back JSON data that'll have those same properties inside of it, that's why
I'm able to access these directly. So it's really, really easy to work with.
The catch is knowing about this if you're working in the .NET world and using WCF Services.
Okay, so we have our function, let me go ahead and end our bracket here.
Now if I run it as is, if you recall, jQuery will try to figure out the datatype, but we actually want it to
be JSON data. So what I'm going to do is leverage the fourth parameter and I'm going to pass in, in fact you
can see that fourth parameter there in the IntelliSense, let's see if I can get that back, there we go, and
so I'm going to pass in that I'd like this to be JSON data. So there's my post, we're going to call up to the
service, we're going to tell it which operation to invoke, we're not passing any data, here's my callback
function, which will simply update the OutputDiv with the FirstName and the LastName, and then we're going to
explicitly say that this should be JSON data. So I'm going to leave Fiddler going here, and you can see it's
empty right now. Now if we run it as is, as I just showed earlier, you're not going to see a whole lot, but let's
make sure that everything works, and you can see John Doe is returned, so that's perfect, that's what we wanted.
But if we go back to Fiddler, we don't see anything because of the localhost thing I talked about.
Let's go ahead and we'll fix that, let's put a dot, we'll hit Enter, this'll load, and now we're going to
invoke it, and John Doe is returned. Now let's look at what Fiddler gives us.
So this is the call when the page loaded. In fact you can see the page right there, here's the call when we
actually did the jQuery script, let me return or remove these guys, and here is the call, which is a post,
which is our post operation. Now you can see what it's calling here, CustomerService.svc/GetCustomers, you
can see that it's application/json as far as what the client is passing up, and that's because we did that
ourselves of course. Here's the data being passed back. So we have, let me open this in Notepad, we have
JSON data. Now as I mentioned by default, WCF will wrap the data returned in this d object.
So you can see we have d:, then we have an array, and the array ends right there, so we have the start and the
end of it. Now the type of data in the array is a customer object, and you can see that it has a FirstName of
John, an ID of 0, LastName of Doe. We also have another type called, which is a customer, FirstName Jane and
LastName of Doe. So the trick here, if you're doing the things in the .NET world and you want to use WCF Services
out of the box, if you see this behavior and you can't figure out why, then let's go back to the code here,
you can't figure out why you can't just say data 0 .FirstName. Well, you might want to pull up something
like Fiddler to check out what the JSON is, and that way you'll know if there's a d that you have that wrapper
object to worry about. Now there is a way to change that, that's beyond the scope of this course, but you
can make it where it just returns the raw JSON without the wrappers, that is possible in WCF.
So that's another example of using the post. That's also an example of using Fiddler, which is an excellent
tool, I use it for everything from AJAX calls to working with Silverlight to working with anything that
exchanges data across the wire.