The final function we're going to talk about available in jQuery that's related to AJAX is actually called ajax.
And if you're a Lord of the Rings fan, it's kind of the one function to rule them all.
As I showed earlier, the load, the get, getJSON, post, all of those rely on the ajax function behind the scenes,
so it's the heavy lifting one that does all the actual work to communicate with a remote site.
So the ajax function has a lot of different properties you can pass in, and by properties, you're going to
see I mean JSON properties, but here's a few of the key properties you can pass when you call this function.
So you can pass what's the contentType of the data going up to the server, is it just multipart form-encoded,
post, is it JSON, is it XML, what do you have there. You can also pass what is the data that you're passing up.
This could be simple strings, it could be JSON data, those types of things.
What's the dataType of the data coming back. Oftentimes with ajax-enabled apps now days, it's JSON, but it
can be other things like XML or HTML. If there's an error, there's a callback you can hook up, a function
that you can assign to the error property. There's a success, when it was successful and when it's just
totally done, there's even a completion you can pass. And you can even influence the type of request made,
is it a get or is it a post. Now an example of using some of the properties is shown here, and there's a lot
of properties, I'll show that at the end of this section, but here's some of the key ones I just mentioned.
So we have the url, but you'll notice that these are marked up in a JSON object, there's the start and end
brackets for that object. So the url is of course what are we calling to get our data.
This could be a REST API, a web service, whatever it may be. The data that's going to be passed up, well in
this case, customer is a JSON object that you'll see in the demo, and this allows us to pass up the data to
the server just like you saw with the get and the post. What's the dataType of the data, of the data being
passed back from the server. It's going to be json data in this example.
If it's a success message, then you can pass that a function. So in this case we're getting back the data
that's returned, the status, which is it an error or not, and then you could get even more details through
the XMLHttpRequest object, which is this third parameter. Now in this case, because we're calling a service,
which is a WCF Service as I mentioned in the post section, it actually wraps the data with this d object in
many cases. So in this case we're returning a single object that has a status of the insert operation and a
message because it might have failed about the insert operation.
Now it was an array, we could get d, do the brackets and get to 0, 1, so on and so forth as I mentioned in the post
section. Now you can also have an error callback, which is very useful, and of course something you typically
want to have, and so this allows you to get to details about the error and either notify the user through a
pop-up alert or maybe some other UI element that you want to show.
Now there's even more JSON properties for this ajax function that you can work with, so let me pop up the
jQuery documentation page real quick and talk through a few of those.
So if you go to the standard api.jquery.com page and then click on the Ajax item on the left here, you can
get to all the ajax functions and then ultimately get to the global ajax function.
So, the ajax function only takes one parameter, and as I just showed earlier, that's a JSON object that has
these properties. Now there's a lot of stuff you can do with this.
You can set whether or not the call is async, which I would recommend leave that as true, but there may be a
few times when you need to change it. You can say if you want to cache it, before the data is actually sent
you might want to do something to the headers that are sent up or you might want to do something to the user
interface right as that call is about to be made. There's a completion callback.
So we have success, we have error, and then you have this complete, which lets you know when everything is
all done. You can set the contentType of the data being sent up to the server.
You can come in and set the data that's passed up, there's even filters you can apply, the dataType coming
back from the server, and you can see the different options that can be passed there.
What's nice about these, and I mentioned this is the get and post, is if you don't pass this, JSON data is
pretty easy to figure out by jQuery, so it'll make intelligent guesses whether it's JSON or XML or HTML for
you, but if you're having problems, you might want to set that dataType.
Moving on down, here's the error function callback we can assign, and the list goes on and on and on with a
lot of different things you can do such as the timeout, getter post, the url, and even username and password
if you want to login to a site. So a lot of different things can be set, they provide a lot of great documentation
here about how to use callback functions like this one. This would be really analogous to what I showed you
with the get and the post where you simply pass in the URL followed by a callback function, but because we're
using the ajax function, we have to do that through these JSON properties.
So, I won't go through all the rest of them, there's a lot here if you ever want to do something called JSONP,
you can even do that through the ajax function. In fact that's what you'd want to go through to work with that.
Very nice, JSONP in a nutshell is a great way to make calls to cross-domain type of services.
So definitely read through this if you're going to be sending data to and from the server and you'd like to
use this more low level API, which is the ajax function in jQuery.