If you're working a lot with JavaScript in the browser then odds are you probably have to handle different
types of events. After all, you need to know when the user clicks on a button or when they select a
different item from a drop-down, or maybe you even want to know when they mouseover a div or something along those lines.
Well if you've done it before by hand and had to deal with cross-browser issues you know it can be a little
more challenging than you would think, at least at first glance.
And that's because depending on how far back you need to go in the browsers as far as the support goes,
it can get a little challenging because the older browsers, especially Internet Explorer, didn't support
the standard at the time. And the newer browsers do so now you'd have to write some code to figure out
which one to do and we'll be talking about that more coming up.
So what we're going to talk about in this module is how jQuery really simplifies handling events,
and not only does it make it easy but it provides a very robust API; and you can handle different types
of events in different ways and we'll talk about several of those ways as we move along here.
So the agenda is we're going to start off by talking about some of the cross browser issues out here
and the challenges that provides us as developers, and then from there we're going to jump right into
jQuery and talk about so what are some of the shortcut functions it has that allow you to handle events.
We'll talk about some of the new on and off type of functions that can be used for binding two events
in a really dynamic way. And then we're going to talk about how events can bubble up and how we can handle
those and provide some efficiencies, especially when it comes to working with a lot of children in a table
or maybe a bunch of children in a div or things like that. So we're going to talk about the live,
delegate, and on functions, and I'll introduce live and delegate—they're a little bit older—mainly so you
know about them in case you come across them on a blog post or something like that, but we'll mainly
focus on the new and preferred API, and that is the on and the off.
And then we'll wrap up by talking about different techniques you can use in jQuery to do hover effects.
So if you've ever handled it by hand with an event you know that you can do things like mouseenter and
mouseleave, and you can do that in jQuery as well and I'll show that.
But there's some built-in things that make it really nice to not only detect the events but also to swap
out styles, swap out CSS classes and things like that. So let's go ahead and jump in and get started
by talking about how jQuery simplifies the process of working with events.