You've seen how we can attach events and event handlers directly to DOM elements throughout this module.
Well jQuery provides some other really nice options that allow us to attach an event handler without really
attaching an event handler. Here would be the scenario. Imagine you have a table that has a lot of rows
in it; let's say it has a couple hundred rows. Well how do you know if the user clicks maybe on the tr
or mouses over it? Well the normal reaction there is we'll write a selector to go find all the trs and
attach an event handler—maybe a mouseenter, a mouseleave, and a click to every tr.
Well if you had 300 rows then of course that means we're going to be adding 300 different event handlers,
and that starts to build up in memory a little bit. So fortunately there are three different options that
you can use in jQuery to handle this a little more efficiently and those three functions are called
live, delegate, and on and we're going to be talking about these in this section.
Now live, delegate, and on as mentioned provide a way to attach event handlers at a higher level and
you probably know that JavaScript, when you click on things or mouseover, if nothing handles it at that
DOM element then it bubbles up by default and a parent will then try to handle it, and then if they don't
have one it bubbles up to its parent. And this is the standard way that events work with JavaScript.
Well live, delegate, and on provide a really unique way to attach an event at a higher level in the DOM
hierarchy so that when a child is clicked or mousedover, or whatever it may be it can actually bubble up.
And so you'll see this provides a really efficient way to handle events in a variety of scenarios.
So in a nutshell what it does is it allows children to be added into a container, such as a div or a table,
and you don't explicitly have to attach an event handler to each child.
Well let's go back to the row example; if you had 300 rows that means that depending on which of these
functions you use you could attach an event handler at a higher level in the DOM hierarchy and as a child
is clicked there is no event handler there, but it'll bubble up and then the parent will detect it.
So let's dive in here and I'll give you some examples of how this works with each of these.
So first up if live; now it's important to know that this is kind of an old API and it's been removed
completely in jQuery 1.9. So if you're using an older version of jQuery then you could certainly use
this, but jQuery 1.9 doesn't even have it at all. So why am I covering it??
Well because you may see this in blog posts or other areas, and although you may not use it after I show
these other options, it's important to know what it's for and how it works and why some of the other
options are better, so we'll go over it just real quick here.
So what you can do is do a selector, and in this case we're going to target everything that has some class
on it and we're going to attach this live binding to it.
And what's going to happen is anything that has some class on it—the click event won't actually be attached
at the DOM element that has some class. Instead what'll happen is it'll bubble all the way up to the
document object and you can see up here—the document object handles events by default.
Now what'll happen is we'll have one function in memory that acts as the event handler, it'll be attached
to the document object and now when any child that has some class is clicked in this case it'll bubble up.
Now you can turn that behavior off by using the die, so a lot of people call this live because it kind of
looks like that; I guess you could officially say it's live because there's a corresponding die but it
really doesn't matter—you say tomato I say tomato. But we say die and click and give it the same function
that was attached and what that'll do is basically detach the click and the event handler from the document object.
So let's look at a more visual example of this.
So you can see that I have some class as my selector and I'm going to attach this live meaning for the
click and you're going to see that ultimately that's going to be attached up on the document object level.
Now imagine that I had a span, and a p tag, and a div, and maybe some others that all have some class.
Well normally if you did .some class for the class selector .click then we would have three different
event handlers attached to a specific function for each of those that eats up a little more memory.
Well because we're doing the live binding here the click event will actually cause a bubble up effect
and the event will actually bubble up to the document object. Now the document object will actually look
for all kinds of events, but in this case it's specifically going to monitor children that were clicked
that have some class on them as a class. And so if it does the click event will be fired and then the event
handler will be called. And so you can see now we only have one event handler and even if we had 1000
elements with some class on it there would still only be one click event handler, so it's very efficient that way.
Now the downside of this is it is bubbling all the way up to the document so let's look at another option.
So a newer version of the kind of live concept is delegate. Now this was added in jQuery 1.4 as you can see
and it's still available in jQuery 1.9 as well. And what it allows you to do is specify a context object—
you're going to see that right in here—that actually is the parent that handles the bubble up events and
then processes those events. So it works as new children are added into its container and will ‘
automatically detect what child was clicked and if it's appropriate, will handle it.
So here's an example of using delegate. So our context is going to be this # or hash Divs, so the ID
with divs on it. We'll say that's just a div that's a container.
We're going to delegate that when any child that's a div is clicked, call this function here.
And then you can undo this by calling un-delegate, it's kind of like the die I just showed you.
Now this works the same
way visually; the difference is it's not going to bubble all the way up to the document so we have this
#Divs for our ID selector, delegate, and in this case someClass is going to be our selector and what's
going to happen is any child of this that has this class on it, when it's clicked it'll bubble up.
So the same premise here. We could have a span, and a p tag, and a div and they might be in this
wrapper div here, and when any of those are clicked they don't have an event handler on them so what'll
happen is it'll bubble up, but instead of bubbling all the way up to the document it's actually going to
go up to our context that we set, which is our divs here. Then if one of those was clicked the click
event handler gets called and we're off and running, so very similar to the whole live binding concept
but more specific and you don't have to bubble up as far.
Now the next one I've already shown earlier in this module and that's the on function.
Now as jQuery grew we had all these different ways we could handle events: we have bind I showed briefly,
delegate we just looked at, live we just looked at, and the problem is it got a little bit confusing
on which should I use in, you know, which scenario. And so I've already shown one example of using on,
very similar to this earlier in the module. Any div on a click, call this function, and that's kind of
the standard way that you'll see on. But it truly is a replacement for bind, delegate, and the whole live binding concept.
And so now we have one API to rule them all and it makes it much easier to just go with one thing and be
able to use it. Now on was actually added in jQuery 1.7 so it's been out for quite a while, and it can be
used for simple things but it can also replace the whole live and delegate concept.
So here's an example of we're going to set a context note and it's almost analogous to what I just showed
with delegate, but things are reversed as far as the parameters.
So in this example we're going to say go find this MyTable ID and find the tbody under it.
On a click of a tr, bubble up to the tbody and this function will now be attached to the tbody.
So just like delegate we can set a context, but this one allows us to I think find a more readable solution.
So on a tbody on click for a tr, invoke this function. Now we could also in the tr we could do that
someClass I just talked about earlier. So this is the preferred way now to do this and so you really
don't need to use bind, live, delegate, or those at all, because you can do everything with on.
So as long as you're on jQuery 1.7 or higher, which odds are you are, then I would recommend you go with on here.
Now you can also map on to multiple types of events and callbacks.
In fact, you can even say in addition to having mouseenter and mouseleave call the same event handler
function, which I showed earlier in this module, you can even map them to different callback functions.
So here's an example of doing that with what we call a map. You'll notice that we say for a tr on
and then we have an object literal here, so here's the start of it, there's the end of it.
We're going to say when the mouseenter fires call this function, when the mouseleave fires call this
function, then if I had more I could keep putting commas. So you could just put all these as one big
stint on as the first parameter and have a single callback or you can do this map and actually map an
event to a specific callback function, so very, very nice to know about and very handy and I think
good for maintenance and productivity over all. So on can be used for simple things like clicks;
it can be used for the bubble up concept, which I'm going to demonstrate here in a moment, and you can
even map events to their own individual callback functions, which is really, really nice.
So now that we've seen the different options let's jump into a demonstration and I'm going to focus on
on because that's what we should be using, but keep in mind that you can do similar things as what I'm
going to demo with the live or the delegate. So let's go ahead and get started here.