In this demonstration we're going to take a look at how we can use the on function to handle events
without actually attaching an event handler to every single DOM element in our target.
So I have a simple table here and you can see it has several rows.
And ill switch over to design view here and you'll see that. So nothing real fancy and the standard way
if we wanted to know when they clicked to handle this would be once we know the document's loaded we
could go find our trs and then we could do click or if we want to use on we could say on click and then
we can give it our function. And then inside of here we could go dig down into for instance, the different
td's or something, but I'll just to show it works—we'll go ahead and say alert and we'll do this, which will
be the tr and we'll grab the HTML.
And so if we run this as we click on say, Tina Smith here, you can see Tina Smith is found and we click
on Jim Leaner and it's found, and
you get the idea there. Well what this is doing is actually attaching an event handler to every single
tr in our table. Now I only have a handful here so it's not a huge deal, but imagine that we had quite a few.
Well that starts to eat up into memory, and especially if you had a lot of these—hundreds or maybe even
thousands—and so there's a more efficient way we can do this. Now the problem kind of worsens if I said
I also want to handle on mouseenter and mouseleave, let's say.
Because now we're going to have three different events and we're going to be attaching this function here for those.
HTR now has kind of three
things going on. And although it should work it's definitely not what we'd want to be after here;
you can see it fired both those as I enter and leave and then I'd have to find a way to click them.
Not very efficient and it works, but we have a better way we can handle this.
So what we can do is instead of actually attaching into every single row we can go select a parent.
Now let's say that our table had an ID of customers. Then we could come back in and we could say find the
ID, so we'll go find customers and then I want to attach either to that, which would be fine, or I could
go down even a little lower and attach to the tbody and I'm going to say on a click for what?
And now I can say in this case a descendent that's a tr or I could even do a td.
Now tads even complicate it more because obviously every row has two tds and if we did it the way we've
learned up to this point and just attach something to every td, then now we're really talking a lot of
different event handlers, especially if you had more than two columns.
So now we're going to say for the customer's tbody on a click of a td and you can see this is a descendent
of the tbody; call this function and we'll grab the HTML inside.
In fact let's just grab the text because now a td would have John Doe and Jim Leaner and things like that.
So we'll go ahead and run this now.
And now as I click on Jim Leaner you'll see we get Leaner because that's what I clicked on there.
And we can get Jim, Patoria, Sapna, and you get the idea.
So a much more efficient approach now, because the tbody, which there is no tbody but the browser will add
it for us—in fact just to kind of demonstrate that
concept if we go in and get to the chrome developer tools—you can hit F12 to do that—and now we can come
down to our table and notice there is a tbody there, and so it's just added dynamically by the browser
and that's why this all works. And so now there is no event actually attached to the tds, it's to
the actual tbody here,
so very, very efficient. Now this is something that I personally like to do a lot.
Any time I have, whether it's divs that're going to have children or some other type of item, this works great.
Now, let me show you another example here. Let's say that we had a button and for this button let's
say that when it's clicked we want to do something like add a new row, so I'll come in and let's give this
an ID of we'll just call it addRow to be really obvious and we'll say Add Row here.
So let's come on in and right up above here we'll go find addRow, and we could say on a click we'll add
a new row into our table. So now I can come in and we can find our table; now I'm going to be doing
the table twice here, so normally what I'll like to do is cache it so let's go ahead and say table =
and we'll do customers. And the reason is I don't want to type customers twice in here and here.
So what we could do now is we could go ahead and from our table we could find the tbody, and that'll
go look in the descendents for the tbody, and then on a click of a td do something.
But what I want to do here is say table., and we can append a new row in here.
Now we know there's a tbody so we could certainly go find again the tbody.
And in fact, we could even cache the tbody up here if we'd like.
And so to make this even easier go ahead and just find the tbody up here and we'll just reuse it.
So now we can just replace that with tbody on click and then here we can say tbody., and we're going to
append in a new row so let's go ahead and just real quick make a new row here.
And we'll do let's say Jane Doe. Okay, so every time we add a row it's going to actually add Jane Doe
every time, but what's cool about this is I don't have to officially attach anything and I'll still be
able to click on these newly added rows. So let's go ahead and run it and see what we get here.
Okay, so we'll Add Row and notice we get Jane Doe and I'm going to add a couple of these.
Now we're going to click and notice it still works, yet I didn't attach an official event handler
to any of these; it's simply bubbling up to the tbody
and then the tbody's handling it. So that's where this gets really nice because if it was a div and it
had children in can now programmatically add children to the collection or if it's a table with rows
I can add rows to the collection and I don't have to worry about adding the event handler, plus it's just
better on memory all the way around. So that's an example of using on in a few different scenarios
and it's definitely a great thing to know about if you work with a lot of children or descendents in a container.