The final thing that we're going to talk about in this module on handling events with jQuery is hover events.
Now I've actually shown a couple different ways to do this with shortcut functions and the bind, but there's
actually a built in hover that we can use and it makes it really, really easy to handle the mouseenter and
mouseout with a minimal amount of code. So let's
take a look here at what we can do. So there's a shortcut hover function.
So it's kind of like combining the mouseenter mouseleave functions; you can actually see that here in the second bullet.
So you make your selector and get that all wired up so that it finds the proper DOM element, you then go
in and call .hover and then you can give it in this case two functions: one to handle when you hover in
or the mouseenter and one for the handler out, which would be equivalent to the mouseleave.
So really simple to do; now there's different versions of this, defend overloads of this functions,
so you'll see in a moment there's different functions we can pass for these different parameters.
So the easiest way to use it is to simply call .hover and then pass in those two functions an you'll
know that the first function is for when you mouseenter and then mouseleave on that second function.
So in this example you can see that we're simply going in, we're doing a jQuery wrapper in that first
function there around this ID selector called target. So we're going to find that DOM object, put it in
a jQuery wrapper with this and we're going to simply change the CSS property of background color.
Now when they mouseout or when the mouseleave is called officially then we're going to go in, call that
second function, and we'll do the same jQuery wrapper and we're going to change the background color it
looks like back to white in this example; so very, very simple to do.
Now if all you wanted to do was change one particular style this would be a pretty good way to go,
but let's say that you want to swap a class on or off of the DOM element.
Well we already know how to do toggle class, I've shown you that actually several times throughout the
course, and toggle class combined with hover provides the ultimate in ease of use and flexibility so here's
an example of doing that. You can actually just pass in one handler, one function, which is the in and the out.
Now this actually fires when they mouseenter and went they mouseleave and you could certainly detect that
with the event object, but the wrapper here around this, you'll see we simply leverage toggle class.
So it really doesn't get any easier than that, you know, you could do this with bind and if you recall
with the bind you can pass in a string the function—or sorry, the event names—and so you could pass
mouseenter space mouseleave. Well that certainly works and you can go that approach, but you know,
with the shortcut here it's like it doesn't get much easier than this.
So we'll call .hover; in this case we're going to do it for paragraph text and we'll simply toggle the
over class as they hover in and out of any paragraph class within the page.
So let me show you a quick demo of what that looks like in action and then we'll kind have go from there
and that'll be the end of this particular module.