In a previous demo in this module I showed how you can use the bind function to wire up multiple events
with a single statement to a particular callback function. So we did that with the bind, you can see that
example right here; so we bound in this case the mouseenter, the mouseleave, and the mouseup to this particular function.
So you could certainly do that to handle the equivalent of a hover and it's really the same thing,
or I could even use the shortcut functions mouseenter mouseleave and they would work as well.
But if we really want to make it super easy to work with then we can handle the hover shortcut and use that.
So let's go ahead and what I'm going to do is we're going to add a selector ultimately and then do .hover,
but let me show you what we want to select.
So we have this simple form we've been working with, which just has two columns in it to represent our
labels and our controls. And so let's say that when they hover over these particular rows we want to put
a kind of a light gray background on it; alright. So we can do that by simply doing the hover and making two functions.
So coming on back up to the JavaScript let's go ahead and first let me show you the tables.
So you can see the table is MyTable and then we have trs. Now that's the only trs in this particular page
so we can just say tr if we want, but of course it's always faster from a performance standpoint with a
selector to give it a starting point so we're going to go ahead and say go find MyTable and then go get
the trs within that. And now we'll say hover. Now from here we simply pass in either one function,
which I'm going to do in a moment or the two representing each type of function.
So let me wrap these down so we can see them clearly; so this first one would represent the mouseenter equivalent.
And we'll do one more. And this will represent our mouseleave.
So let's say that we just want to put that kind of light gray background on it, so we can just simply take
the object that was passed to us at this point, which would be this, go to our CSS and say let's change
the background color and we'd like to change that to kind of a light gray here.
And when they mouseout or call the equivalent of that, which is mouseleave, we'll go back to a white
background in this particular example. Alright, so let's go ahead and try that out
and you should see as we hover over the different rows it'll automatically highlight them and it's a
really subtle highlight but its there. So you can see that now when they're in this it makes it really
easy to kind of keep track of where you're at. Now in this example, you know, this is not so much a data
type table, but you could certainly use this for when you have the equivalent of an Excel spreadsheet as
an example and it makes it really nice to highlight that row that they're working on.
Alright; now while that particular code works fine it's quite a bit more code than I might want to do
unless you know, maybe I want to change just some individual styles—the cursor or something like that,
then this would be fine. But if we move up top to our CSS area I have this light highlight and this is
a little bit darker gray to make it a little easier to see, and what I'd like to do is show you the ease ire
way to do this. So we can come back down and instead of doing this way let's go ahead and comment that out.
Let's add a comment here: Using hover. And then we'll come on into here and we're basically going to do
the same thing, so we're going to come in, we'll find MyTable tr and we'll hover, but we're going to do
a single function this time. Much easier, because now all I have to do as shown earlier, is we can come
in and wrap this and toggleClass and we can pass in that LightHighlight class.
Now this is going to do the exact same thing—it'll be a little bit darker than this gray.
Let's go ahead and try it out. So you can see now that as we highlight that it highlights those different
rows really easily here. So super, super
easy to implement. And you know, you have the flexibility of handling the unique mouseenter and the
unique mouseout, or if you just want to kind of treat it, let it do its thing, and use toggleClass this is
probably the easiest way to do it, so at this point I've shown you how you can use the shortcut functions;
mouseenter, mouseleave; I've shown you how you could use bind—that was shown up here, and then finally
we just looked at how you can use hover. So there's three and there's even more than that I'm sure I can
think of another way, but different ways to work with this. I think the flexibility there is one of the
strengths of jQuery—yeah, sometimes it's a little difficult to know, so which is the better way?
Well in my opinion this is the best way if you want to do a simple hover, because I prefer to use CSS classes
you know, whenever I can; it makes it nice and easy. Alright, now to end this video let me go and and show
you one more little shortcut function that's kind of related. I'm going to come and comment this guy out.
We're going to grab this code, and I'm going to do something that's similar here.
Alright, so let me comment this back in. Scoot that over a little bit.
Hover is obviously the mouseenter, mouseleave, but there's also another one called toggle.
And that'll call other functions as well; in fact, you can have more than one function with a toggle.
So every time you click it, it could do something different—click, click, click, click, click.
So if I run this, now notice as I mouseover nothing happens here, but now I'm going to click on the row
and you can see that it highlights it, when I click it again it turns it off.
Now I don't know that that's real applicable to rows per say, but while we were at it I wanted to show
how it really is using the same exact code, it's just now it toggles it based on when we click so first
time we click this gets applied, second time we click that gets applied, and then let me do a third to
show you how this works.
And I'm just going to type in the name yellow here and make it kind of obvious.
So now as I go in, and keep in mind this could, you know, probably be on a div or maybe a row of column
or data, but I'll click, we'll click again, and we'll click again, and so you can see every function you
put it toggles through those different options.
Very nice when you need it. So that's just kind of a bonus one that looks like hover, but you know,
it's a little bit different there. So that's an end to our section on handling events in jQuery, and
specifically on how we can handle the hover, and then there's your quick look at the toggle shortcut.