In this module we talked about how jQuery can be used to really simplify our life when it comes to
handling events in a cross browser way. So we talked about how in Internet Explorer IE8 really and earlier
they handle events and attach to events quite a bit differently than all the other browsers.
IE9 gets it right and makes it much easier but there's still going to be IE8 and earlier hanging around.
So jQuery takes all that out of the picture. It provides several shortcut functions; we talked about
some of them such as click, dblclick, mouseenter, mouseleave, and more.
And provides functions such as bind, which is more of a low level API that allows you to pass in one or
more event names that you want to bind to a particular DOM element that we found with a selector.
What's nice about bind is you simply separate those event names with a space and it automatically
will call the function that you define as either—either of them if there's two, or if there's more, any of
them I guess—are triggered. Unbind we also talked about can be used to clear events or strip those off
of a given DOM object. You can, if you pass no parameters, it strips everything or you can pass specific
event names to just remove those. From there we went into the live and the delegate and these two
were used to allow future children added into the DOM programmatically to automatically be associated with
an event and an event function. The difference was live was in jQuery 1.3 and it bubbles events from
those children up to the document object, which ultimately handles triggering the event and calling the
event handler I should say. The delegate goes in and it actually allows you to supply a selector context
so instead of having to bubble everything up all the way to the document object, which could be expensive
depending on how deep your events are going, delegate allows this selector context so that it only bubbles
up to that specific parent—hopefully that's just one or two levels up from these children that are
ultimately leading to the event firing. So those are really, really nice though if you want to just hook
things up once, and as I showed with the phone demo, allow different phones to be added as they click and
not have to always add additional code to wire those new text boxes or whatever it may be off to an event function.
The final thing we talked about was the hover and I showed how hover is really just a shortcut function,
but it simplifies the mouseenter mouseleave and provides a really simple way to really to either pass it
two functions representing both the mouseenter and mouseleave or one function and then you can combine
that with things like toggleClass, so jQuery really provides a lot of simplicity and ease of use when it
comes to events, and it even makes it easy to work with the event object, which we also talked about
and get to some of those properties cross browser. So one of the things I've been mentioning throughout
the course, I would recommend that if you get some time head off to jquery.com and check out the events
section because there's even more in there that wasn't covered here; this is a kind of introduction to
it to get you started and the more you know the more powerful you are as a developer, so I would
definitely take the time to go explore what's there so that you know what's available.