Let's take a look at what jQuery brings to the table when it comes to building JavaScript enabled
applications that have to deal with events. So first off a question for you, what type of JavaScript code
do you write to handle a button click event? Think that through real quick.
Now I'm not talking about doing it the HTML way 100% JavaScript and if you've been doing this very long
you probably said well Dan, that's a trick question, and it is. It depends on the browser because each
browser does it a little bit differently depending on the category, and let's break those categories
down, it's pretty simple. You have IE8 and earlier, and in Explorer8 and earlier, and pretty much everything
else; IE9 included in the everything else. They all
do it differently between those two categories so most browsers will simply take the DOM object and
allow you to say addEventListener and then give it the name of the event and a callback. That's the
standard way to do it, that's what you do in Chrome, and Safari, and Firefox, and all the major browsers out there.
Well in IE8 or earlier it's a totally different way to do it. Something Microsoft came up with that's
now fortunately remedied in IE9, but there's still a lot of IE8 and earlier out there and will be.
So what you do is you take the DOM object and you say attachEvent and you'll notice that the name of the
event you want to attach to is even different than the one above, which is click, so you say onclick instead of click.
So that right there can make it confusing because you have got to get it right; it's a string and you have
to, you know, make sure there's no problems there. So what jQuery brings to the table is it wraps both
of these pieces of functionality and it abstracts that out from you as the developer.
You don't have to worry about it; it just automatically takes care of knowing which one of these to call
based upon the browser. So to wrap up this particular section of the module let's just do
a real quick review if you're newer to this whole concept of events before we go on to talk about some of
the jQuery shortcuts for handling events. So events are just a way to notify that something has happened.
So an example would be a user clicks a button, you as the JavaScript developer need to know that they
clicked the button. Now, if you're coming from a Java or a .NET background—some other language that
handles events—then you know, this is old news to you, but that's all we're talking about is you focus
on a textbox, we want to know; you mouseover something, we as the application want to know.
So jQuery provides a very rich API for cross browser event model support across all the major browsers
and some very compact syntax—a lot of different options and some cool stuff that we're going to talk about
that to do it with raw JavaScript would be pretty difficult. So in the next section we're going to be
talking about some of these shortcuts and talk about how we can hook up to events in a cross browser way.