Before actually jumping into how to use some of the JQuery functions, I wanted to show the traditional
way that we write JavaScript to be able to handle events. So I have a very simple form here and you'll
notice at the bottom we have a SubmitButton and what I'd like to do is add a little bit of code to
programmatically hook up; now we could certainly come in and we could do it the JavaScript or the HTML way,
however, I want to do it programmatically. Now the first thing that I have to worry about is I'd
have to know so when is the page loaded? So I'd have to deal with the on load and handle that with IE
or with all the other browsers. Now what I'm going to do to get around that is one of the easy ways to
know when it's loaded—it's just down here at the bottom. We can come and put a script tag so I'm going
to put it right outside of my form actually. And then inside of here we can add some code to handle the
events, I'm just going to put Handle events the old-fashioned way.
So this is what the code would look like. First off we'd probably want to go get our button, so you'll
notice it's called SubmitButton. So we'd say document.getElementById.
And then from there we need to know which browser are we in; are we in IE8 or earlier or are we in anything else?
Well the easiest way to do that is you could just come in and say hey, does the document support the addEventListener?
If it does support that API then we can go ahead and do it with what most browsers expect, and if it doesn't
we'll have to do it the IE way. So now that we have the button we can say hey, let's go ahead and add
an EventListener for the click event and then I'll just put an in line function; we'll just alert Clicked Button.
Okay, so that's kind of the standard way to do it, but as we know IE handles it differently, so we'd
have to do attachEvent and onclick and then we can give it our function.
And I'm going to go ahead and this time say Clicked IE Button so that we know the difference.
Okay, so that's kind of your two options for attaching EventListeners, and of course depending on the
event you would substitute in a different name here. So we go find the button, we then check does this
browser support this API, if it does we're going to use it, otherwise we're going to fall back and assume
that Internet Explorer. Okay, so if we go ahead and run this as is,
right now I'm in Chrome and you'll see we got Clicked Button because it supports the official addEventListener.
Well let's go ahead and grab that URL,
and we'll open the same thing up
in Internet Explorer
and run it and you'll see we get Clicked IE Button.
So you can see it's not that hard to work around, however, it still is quite a bit of code and it'll really
make you appreciate what I'm going to show in the next section of this module, which is some of the jQuery shortcuts.