Let's take a look at what jQuery offers us out of the box when it comes to handling events in a cross
browser way so that you're not pulling your hair out worrying about which browser works and which doesn't
for the different attachments.
So there are a lot of different shortcuts that are built in to jQuery that automatically hide from you
the cross browser issues that were mentioned in the previous section.
So here's just a few of them: click, blur, focus, you'll notice there's even a dblclick, which is a little
trickier to do in JavaScript without—you'd have to set up interval times and things.
But different mouse events and key events and all that type of stuff, and what you can do with these
is find your object using the selector, simply hit .click, .blur, whatever it is based on the object
and then have a callback function; very, very simple. So you can get a lot of details about this at the
URL below: api.jquery.com, so let me go ahead and pull up the browser and show you what's at that site.
So the event documentation for jQuery is actually really good.
A lot of details, all the API functions are called—or covered I should say—and there's even demos with most of them.
So if I scroll on down you'll notice that we have this bind, we're going to talk about that a little bit
later—that's not a shortcut function, that's actually what the shortcut function's called behind the scenes.
But here's blur, change, click, dblclick; we'll talk about some of these others later—delegate, and die,
and live, but in addition to the shortcut functions there's also this event object so you'll notice that
you can get to different properties of the event, such as if you want to know the pageX and pageY—the mouse
position relative to the document. Then what they've done is the event object that's passed when you
use one of the shortcut functions—such as mousedown or mouseup—will automatically pass you an event
object that's wrapped with jQuery wrapper and automatically gets you into the appropriate property
based upon the target browser. Now, the event object itself is even different across the different browsers, or can be.
So that's a nice thing. So if you want to get to the target for instance, there's only one way to do
that if you go through jQuery so you don't have to worry about the hassle of doing it on your own.
So here's where you can get to the different API's; now I'm not going to have time to cover every single
one of these but let's do a real quick demo of say dblclick.
So if you go in to dblclick you'll notice that you have to give it a handler, and the handler, which is the
callback will allow an event object to be passed in. And then scrolling on down here's how we use it,
it's very simple. So we grab the target, in this case in other words the DOM object wrapped with a jQuery wrapper.
We call dblclick and here's our callback. Now we could pass an event object right into here if we wanted,
but in this case we're just going to pop up an alert. So at the bottom of this we have a little better
example where we have a particular DOM element we're going to find and then we're going to attach the
dblclick function to it and have it our callback. Now you'll notice when it's dblclicked on the target
we're going to go ahead and toggle the class called dbls. We're going to switch it back and forth between
different items so here's dbl actually, which is a yellow background.
So I'm going to come down, we'll dblclick it, you'll see it change to yellow, I'll dblclick again,
that'll take that class off into the toggle and we're back to where we were.
So that's an example of the documentation, and with the events it's really nice because there's just a lot
of these shortcuts that you probably won't have memorized of course, that's where you can go to look.
So now that we've seen a few of the shortcuts and how you can get more documentation about them let's
look at a quick example here.
So the click is one of the more common ones, and as shown even with the dblclick its are very similar.
You have a handler and that handler can even have an event object passed if you'd like.
Well, in this example we're going to go find an ID selector so we're going to go find myID, whatever that
is, attach our click to it, identify our callback function, and then in this case we're just going to pop up an alert.
So nothing real fancy on this particular example. Another example that is shown
here, and so you'll notice that we call click, but in this case we target some other objects click.
So you can actually trigger events, there is a trigger function actually, or in this case if we just want
to trigger in essence the click event, then we're going to say hey, when this one is clicked we're also
going to cause this one to be clicked. So click in other words is not just for receiving the data,
but you can actually trigger these events on other objects if that fits your particular application.
So it makes it very easy to work with that way. So let's take a look at using some of these shortcut
functions in an application web page.