Let's take a look at how we can use the different jQuery shortcut functions to easily attach to an object
and hook that up to an event handler for events like click and some others.
So I have a form here
that's just laid out using a really simple table structure; if you like divs, by all means, you can do that too.
Going back to the source, the traditional way we kind of wire up this button here is we come in to the HTML
and we do onclick = and we give it some functions, so we'll just call this SubmitButton_Click.
And then we come up and add our script block.
And then finally add our function. And let's just put an alert to get it going to start.
Okay, so that's kind of the traditional way and there's nothing wrong with that, it still works fine,
that works cross browser very nicely, and if we go ahead and run this guy
you'll see that when we click it we get Clicked Button.
So if that's all we need to do then you could certainly go that route.
Now the challenge with this, and I'm kind of anti hooking up events through code now days this way
because I like to have one place I can look, so generally I prefer actually to do it through code because
then if I want to change things I have one place instead of having to scan a big HTML document.
But there's absolutely nothing wrong with what we just did, it certainly works.
So let me go ahead and take that out and let's do it the jQuery way.
Now we'd have two options here if we want to hook to this button and do an event handler for the click,
then I could come down into the script block that we used earlier in this module for a demo where I
showed kind of the old way of doing it, but let's go ahead, this is a good reason to use the ready function.
So let's go ahead and go back to that. We'll wrap the document object and say .ready and we'll have our function.
Okay, because that way I know everything's loaded, but again you can always do it different ways,
but that's a good example where the ready function's available.
Now what I like to do is I'll often times have my own custom function in here, I'm just going to call it
WireEvents to keep it real simple. And then when I know it's ready I'll simply call WireEvents, and then
in WireEvents we can come down and find our SubmitButton and we can go ahead and do an ID selector to get to it.
Now we can get into all the different event shortcut functions that are available with jQuery.
So obviously for a button I'd probably want to go ahead and do click, see you notice this takes our handler.
And we could do the same thing as we did before.
Okay, so that would kind of be the jQuery way, and you know, if you don't like putting the WireEvents
like I did you can certainly put this up in the ready as well, but in a real live app what will typically
happen is there might be quite a bit of things you wire up and you might sense some CSS dynamically based
on the user, so I generally like to break that out into functions to make it easier to maintain.
So let's go ahead and run that.
And we'll go ahead and grab Clicked Button.
Now that's not real impressive, let's go ahead and take to the next level instead of saying Clicked Button.
Let's go ahead and grab the value from let's say the first name and last name.
So we have FirstNameTextBox and LastName. And let's say that we'd like to just write those right below
the button here. In fact I'll do it right to the right of the button in the form.
So we'll just put a simple div and we'll give it an ID of DivOutput.
Okay, so we'll come in here and let's go find DivOutput and we can simply do the HTML or text, and I'm
just going to go ahead and update the text and keep it simple in this example.
And now we need to grab our text boxes, so what I'm going to do to kind of make it easier to read is we'll
just say var value = and we'll grab our FirstNameTextBox and we're going to grab val.
We talked about that briefly in one of the previous modules in a demo, but that's the easy way to with
jQuery get the value of that when an event has happened and you're dealing with form input controls.
And we can come in and do LastNameTextBox; do the same thing. And let's call this—actually I meant to call
that first name—and lastNameVal; keep it simple.
Okay, so pretty standard code, all jQuery though. We have the ready function that fires that calls
WireEvents; WireEvents is now going to wire up programmatically to our click button so we're going to
keep it out of the markup in this case and do it programmatically.
When that gets called we'll go ahead and go into here, grab that FirstName and LastName value and then
concatenate them together. It should update that div down there at the bottom.
So let's go ahead and run this.
And let's just do John Doe. And you can see it outputs it like you would expect.
Now that's just the first example of using the click.