Now that we've seen the click let's go ahead and add a little bit more.
Maybe when they select a different value from our select here, our dropdown, we might want to do something
specific when that particular event fires. Now again, doing it the kind of normal way we could come in
and say onchange, but we're going to go ahead and do it the jQuery way.
So in the WireEvents I'm going to come in and we'll say Handle select and we'll go ahead and go and find
that for our states.
So let me go ahead and I'm going to change this ID to StatesSelect—make it a little more obvious.
Alright, so when we come in, you know, of course we don't want to do a click on this—wouldn't make much
sense—but we can come in and we can do a change. Now the change does the same type of thing.
We can have event data that's passed in or if we don't need it we can just go ahead and handle it directly.
Now I'm just going to go ahead and handle it directly with no event object.
And there we have our change. Now when the change fires what do we want to do with it?
So what we want to do is obviously grab the value of our select and work with that.
Now, the easiest way to get that is when the change is fired then I'll be passed in also the object that changed.
And so we can actually come in and say this and we can grab a val.
So let's go ahead and we'll just pop that up in an alert just to see it in action.
And let's run it.
And you can see we get the value that was clicked, so very nice and very easy.
I didn't have to worry about getting the selected index or anything fancy; you can see I could just get
directly to that object without having to, you know, retype that ID and look it up again in the DOM.
Now here's an interesting thing though with change; it actually works not just on selects in jQuery,
it actually works with input controls or text blocks.
And so we can come in—or text areas I should say—we could come in and let's come on to here and let's just
add a kind of a bogus class here. I'm just going to call this MyInput.
And I'm going to go ahead and put that on two of these. I'm also going to put it on the select.
I'm going to demonstrate the concept here. So we now have MyInput on a text box, a text area, and a select.
And so coming back up what we can do now is instead of saying only find this ID we could do a class
selector on MyInput. Now whatever changes will get the val.
Now watch what happens here, this is pretty cool,
and something that you just out of the box can't really do with JavaScript.
So let's go ahead and take that off and I'm just going to mouseout and you can see the value—there is no value.
We're going to go to John—I'm now going to mouseout, now I didn't put it on that one so it shouldn't do
anything; see it doesn't. Doe, now this one should trigger it; it did.
And then This is my comment, mouseout. So you can see that the change actually can be used much like we
would do with a key press down or key press up, or focus or loss focus; it makes it really easy to work with this.
Plus, it also works with the select. Now I don't know about you but I find that pretty cool because it
makes it really easy if there is a scenario where I need to know multiple things are changing because
I might change a style or whatever it may be.
As an example let's say that we do have a style up here; well actually let's just reuse our highlight—
that's what I was just going to do, forgot that was up there.
So let's come in; instead of just alerting the value—we can do that too—but let's go ahead to that element
and we can do addClass, Highlight, which will set the background color.
So now once they've filled out particular aspects of the form—the first one doesn't have it so it won't'
do anything—Doe; now once it shows the alert it's going to highlight what they've changed in the document.
And you can see it's now highlighting everything; now you may or may not want that behavior or that particular
color, but you can see what can be done very, very easily using jQuery and the change function.