The next thing we'll look at now that we've seen the click and the change is some of the mouse shortcuts
that are available within jQuery to handle events; makes it really, really easy.
So I have just a div down here and let's say that when we interact with that div we want to maybe do something.
We want to update that HTML; we might change the background, something to that nature.
So two things I want to show: number one I'm going to show the shortcut functions, but I also want to
show the event object; we haven't really talked about that yet, I'm going to show kind of how that works.
So the first thing I'm going to do is let's go find MyDiv, and then once we've found MyDiv let's go to the
different mouse options. So you see we have mousedown, mouseenter, mouseleave, all the way on down to mouseup there.
So quite a bit of functionality built in out of the box. So let's say that when we have mouseenter we'd
like to execute a function. And I'm going to chain onto that; we want to do mouseleave, another function.
And let's go ahead and we'll leverage our highlight class to highlight the background of that particular div.
So the easiest way to do that of course is we can do the toggle class.
Now we can certainly do addClass as well but since we want to only add it when they mouse in and out
it's a lot easier to go with toggle class; otherwise they'd have to do an addClass here and removeClass here.
Now there's going to be some little code duplication to start but we'll talk about that.
So we're going to do this. and we'll do toggleClass, and then just to get the demo working let's go ahead
and cut and past that, and definitely we would want to re-factor this—right off the bat that should raise
an alarm; we have two kinds of code that are the same. I'm actually going to show you an even better
way to do this with less code when we get to the little feature section in this module covering the bind and
unbind—really useful. Now we certainly could re-factor this out, let's get it going and then we can do that as well.
So we'll mouseenter, should show it yellow; mouseout show take that yellow off and that's going to
highlight this particular div here.
Alright, and there we go; you can see it in action.
Now we might also want to go in; let's say when we mouseover we want to change the cursor, well that will
be easy to do, we have the object. We can go to the CSS property or function I should say, and we can
say cursor and let's change it to a hand, which is the pointer.
Now that'll automatically change it; you'll see as we mouse in and out we change to a hand to allow the user to click on
it whenever they'd like. Now let's go ahead and we may also want to redo some of this.
So let's go ahead just for the sake of showing it so I feel better, let's make a new one called Toggle.
And this is going to take the object that we're working with, so this—we'll just call it div.
And what we can do is simply take div, whatever it is, and notice if we do div right here .toggleClass
we're not going to get any IntelliSense. Let's run that as is; we'll see what happens here.
So we'll pass Toggle and we'll pass this. So at least we have the functionality in one place.
Okay, so let's go ahead and run
that as is. And you can see it still works.
So the downside of this is you're not going to get IntelliSense because at this point it doesn't really
know it's a jQuery object; now you could certainly come in and what I would do actually in this case is
instead of wrapping it here it's probably going to be easier to simply do a wrapper here so that in this
case Visual Studio knows about it—now we're back to our IntelliSese and that way we don't double wrap it or
something like that. Let's run it one more time and we're still back in business here.
Okay, so that's an example of using the mouseenter and the mouseleave and it's just as simple for the others.
Now, a little bit more though I want to wrap up with, and that is we haven't talked about passing the actual
event object into any of this stuff. And so as an example when this function is called; there is an event
object that's available. In fact I showed that a little bit earlier.
We went out to the jQuery site and I showed you we can get to things like the current target of the event,
the pageX, the pageY, there's a source target—there we go, right there.
And so you can get to all that stuff directly. So let's go ahead and say that also on this div—we're
going to chain one more here—we'll do a mouseup, we'll pass in a function, but this time I want to just
pass an e, you can name an event and call it whatever you want.
But now we can get to event data about this. And so what's nice is we can go in and let's just change
maybe the HTML of the div; so we already know the div, we've selected it so we could say this, and actually
it's not going to—we could just do the text—and we could say e, well let's just do this.
Let's do X is e.pageX. Now you'll notice you don't get IntelliSense here for the event object so I often
just will run out to the jQuery docs to grab that. And likewise if we wanted, we're really feeling like
showing everything we can go ahead and do the Y here.
Alright, let's run that now. And now I can mouse in and out but when I click it actually updates the
coordinates of where I clicked; you can see as I click around it just continues to update that.
Move up towards the top it gets pretty small on the Y.
Very, very easy to do. Now the other thing you can get to here that's nice is the target.
Now if we just do e.target and run
you see that it just gives us the actual object of this particular item,
but remember we talked about the adder function so we could say target, and let's try to grab the ID
of this and let's see what happens here.
Okay, now why do we get an error? Hopefully by this point in the course you know.
Okay, the answer is yes, this is giving us the target, but you notice when—let me run this one more time—
that it was the raw object—it's the raw DOM object, and the HTML div element.
So if we want to get to the jQuery features we always need to wrap that with a jQuery wrapper.
Now we can get to whatever we want; I'm just going to say go to ID in this case using the adder function.
Now let's run it. You'll see we get to MyDiv.
So I've pointed that out a couple times in the different demos, but it's just one of those things to be
aware of that when jQuery passes you things such as this you're getting the raw object.
When it passes you the event and you get the target or the current target property then you're getting
the raw object, so you always need to put it in a jQuery wrapper if you want to get to the jQuery functionality there.
So that's an example of what we can do with the mouseenter, the mouseleave, the mouseup, all that type of
stuff; very, very easy to do, and you know, what's nice about this is let's say that in addition to this
guy that as a user mouses over each row we want to go ahead and highlight that as well.
Well remember we can always put a comma and now we're going to say on this selector, match my div, and match
the all tr tags.
So if we run it, it may not be great colors here but you'll see that it highlights all the rows plus our div
and that's just amazingly simple compared to the normal code you typically write if you do this with
just custom JavaScript; very nice, very easy to work with. So that is a summary on some of the different
functions that are available; the shortcut event functions and how we can use the mouse events and
actually handle the event object to get to to some of the different data that's available.