Up to this point you've seen how we can use jQuery shortcut functions to handle different types of events
very easily in a cross browser manner, so it really saves you a lot of hassle compared to if we had to
write this code from scratch and deal with IE6 through 8 and modern browsers and mobile browsers and all that fun.
Well behind the scenes with the shortcut functions is actually a core jQuery function called on, and that's
what we're going to talk about in this section is what the on function is and how you can use it, and I'll
also introduce kind of the inverse of it, which is called off.
Now the on function's very simple, it allows you to define the event or events you'd like to attach to
and you'll see you can do that right here as a string such as the click.
And then you define the handler. So in this example down here we're going to say when the ID of my div
is clicked, so on the click of that div let's call this function.
Now the first time I ever saw this on I hadn't really seen it before in a lot of other areas and it
didn't make a lot of sense to me—I'm like on, what does that have to do with events?
Well you have to read it kind of like a sense. MyDiv on click called this function and that's how you can
think of it and then it made sense. Now this was added in jQuery 1.7 so I've mentioned the bind function
a few times earlier, and bind is something that you could also use in jQuery but the recommended approach
with jQuery 1.7 or higher is on. In fact, it is the core event function if you will that's built into jQuery.
But that's all we have to do is simply give it our selector, give it the event or events, and I'll show
you how we can handle multiple events in a moment and then give it the callback.
Now if I wanted to pass the event object to get some data such as the target element and things like that,
I could do that as well, but in this case we don't really need it we're going to assume.
Now the opposite of on is off. What if you want some buttons that have click event handlers to be
disabled for whatever reason because maybe the forms not valid and they can't submit it.
Well, there's an off and it takes the event that you want to turn off.
So as an example if we had a ID of tests when it's clicked we want to call some handler, and let's say
that for whatever reason I want to turn off that click event, then I could just say test off.
And now what that'll do is turn off not only the click but any other events that are attached to that
particular DOM element. Now if you want to remove specific events such as just the click because
maybe I had a mouseenter and a mouseleave attached as well, then we could do off and you pass in the
event or events. Now you'll see that you just separate if you have multiples here with a space and
we're going to see that in just a moment when we handle multiple events with on.
But that's what off does. Now this only something you'll need when you want to sort of detach events
of course; you may not use this one nearly as much as on but it's nice to know about.
Now if for some reason you're working with jQuery 1.6 or something less than the 1.7 that I mentioned
earlier for on, then there's a bind I mentioned, there's also an unbind, so off is kind of the newer
version of unbind. But if you're on 1.7 or higher, which you probably are, then I'd recommend using on and off.
Now you can also come in and bind to multiple events and this is actually kind of handy in some cases,
so let's say that when they mouseenter or mouseleave on a particular div I want to call a function to
toggle the entered class on and off, so when mouseenter is first triggered then if entered is not there
toggleClass will add it, then when mouseleave is triggered entered is already on it so we'll remove it.
So it's a very simple way to handle two events in kind of one go here.
So that's the basics of how on can be used and we're going to jump into a demo now of using it.
But there's some other cool ways it can be used as well, which I'll be showing just a little bit later in
this module but until then let's jump into a demonstration and see how we can actually use on and off.