Up to this point you've seen how we can handle events using the shortcut functions like mouseenter,
mouseleave, mouseup, and I chain those together and it works out really well.
Well behind the scenes these are actually delegating to on; in fact, I'm going to show
a nice source code viewer here that'll help you see
exactly what the jQuery functions do. So if I go type in jquery source viewer
this will take me off to the jQuery source viewer home here.
And now I could switch to the latest version of jQuery. And as I type click this will let me see the
actual source code that jQuery runs behind the scenes. You'll notice it's actually delegating to on.
Now we could even navigate if you want to see all the details for on.
Now likewise if I wanted to look at the focus, it's also going to on; in fact, all of these are.
We can do the mouseenter and notice it's also going to on. So really
on is the core event handler function that's behind the scenes. So what I'm going to do to demonstrate
it is let's come on in and tweak this a little bit, so I'm going to comment this code out that we had before.
And let's look at using bind and on. Now bind is the original version that we had prior to jQuery 1.7.
So if you are in an earlier version because you're kind of stuck there for now then you're going to have
to go with bind if it's prior 1.7. But 1.7 or greater you can actually go with our on.
And so now I can come in and do the following: we can go find the same thing as we did up here and so
we'll find MyDiv, and then I could do bind if I want and then give it the events.
So we could say mouseenter, mouseleave, and the last one up here is mouseup.
Now we're going to be able to handle all three of those and that's all you would do with bind.
Now to change this to the modern way to do it you simply change that to on, so not a big surprise there.
Now when these events are fired what are we going to do? Well we need a function so we're going to handle
the function and pass an event arc here. And that'll represent our event object that gets raised.
So when mouseenter, mouseleave, or mouseup are fired we're going to come in and do something with those.
So I'm going to get to the div that was actually triggered here and we'll say toggleClass and I'm going to
toggle a class we had up earlier called highlights, so just as a quick review it just changes the background to yellow.
And so we're going to use the built in jQuery toggleClass to either add the class or remove the class
based on the presence or lack of presence. So we'll go ahead and do highlight there.
Now I'm also going to go in and change—we're just going to use CSS for this one but I could certainly
do it through a class. And I'm going to change the cursor—let's put that in quotes actually.
Now I could certainly go in to the highlight and change that, but in this case I'm saying I always want
it to be there. I generally prefer to use classes but this will get the job done.
Now I want to do something really special in this case—if its mouseenter or mouseleave this is all I want
done, but if it's a mouseup I want to do what we did earlier and grab this text right here and write out
pageX and the pageY location. So we'll come in here and put that but I only want to do it if it's a mouseup.
So we could say if (e.type == ‘mouseup') and that'll let us know that it's just this one event, then we'll
come in and we could handle the mouseup and we're going to write the text of the div and update it to
the pageX and the pageY; in other words, where'd you click with the mouse?
And that's all we have to do to actually go in and use the on. Now if at any point I wanted to come in
and turn things off then we would do the same thing; we could say MyDiv or we could even cash that in
a variable since we've already selected it and say off and then if we wanted to turn, for instance,
mouseup off we would just do that and mouseup would be off. Now If I just put off it would turn off
everything in this case. So I'm going to go ahead and just leave that commented out here.
So now if we run this what'll happen
is I can now mouseover the MyDiv and it should automatically change it,
and then if we click in it when the up actually fires for it then we'll be able to see that and write out
the different pageX and pageY.
Alright, so there we go; so there's the hover affect that we had earlier, so nothing really impressive,
we're just using the on right now and then if I click it notice that it now writes out the X:73 Y:22
and wherever I click it'll update it of course.
And now we're able to handle all of that in one simple location using the on.
Now you can certainly use the shortcut functions if you'd like; it's an alternative—it's really up to you
on what you'd prefer. I do think the shortcut functions are nice in the sense that I don't have to
type any quotes, but in this case I prefer the on because now I can actually go in and handle multiple
events as you see. So that's an example of the role of on and as I mentioned, you could change this
to bind as well and it would still work but that would only be prior to jQuery 1.7.
The modern way to do it is to use the on.